<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Savas Labs</title>
    <description>We design digital products that users love
</description>
    <link>https://savaslabs.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://savaslabs.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 20:15:54 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 20:15:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savas Brings on Another Front-end Developer</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-am-i&quot;&gt;Who am I?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello Savas Labs fans! My name is &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/madeline-streilein/&quot;&gt;Madeline Streilein&lt;/a&gt;, and I am one of Savas’ two brand new Junior Front-end Developers (&lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/alex-manzo/&quot;&gt;Alex Manzo&lt;/a&gt; also joined our burgeoning front-end squad under the tutelage of &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/anne-tomasevich/&quot;&gt;Anne Tomasevich&lt;/a&gt; - keep an eye out for their introduction). Some random facts about me: I love stone fruit, humidity, satirical news, and using Slack notation on all messaging platforms. I also opened a day spa in my home when I was in elementary school. It wasn’t &lt;em&gt;_not_&lt;/em&gt; profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-did-i-come-from&quot;&gt;Where did I come from?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.projectshift.io/&quot;&gt;Project Shift&lt;/a&gt;, if you haven’t heard, is a software engineering fellowship here in Durham. I am a proud graduate of Cohort 5. Prior to Project Shift, I came from the land of electoral politics, a field that relies heavily on technology (from data analytics and predictions to voter contact and volunteer recruitment) to mobilize voters and volunteers in the days, weeks, and months leading up to an election. In my most recent role, I ran a statewide peer-to-peer texting program to get North Carolinians to the polls. I experienced first hand how thoughtful technology can catalyze civic engagement, and on the flip side, how platforms that weren’t built with the user in mind could cause enough frustration to dissuade volunteer participation and annoy an on-the-fence electorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-am-i-choosing-to-sit-behind-a-computer-when-i-could-be-hitting-the-pavement-or-training-organizers&quot;&gt;Why am I choosing to sit behind a computer when I could be hitting the pavement or training organizers?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I ask myself, possibly more frequently than I’d prefer, what is the best use of my time and potential skills? Am I contributing enough to causes that matter? Am I contributing in a way that is actually helpful and not harmful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer at which I’ve finally arrived is this: I believe technology has the potential to alter our habits as individuals, as a society, and as a species positively, more quickly, efficiently, and sustainably than through other means of change that may come to mind. I knew I had to switch industries to help build better solutions. Using technology to maximize positive impact, I learned through the interview process, is also part of a developing vision at Savas Labs. Stay tuned for an upcoming announcement with more specific articulation of those goals from team leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-did-i-choose-savas&quot;&gt;Why did I choose Savas?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose Savas for many reasons — especially the team. I’ve seen my coworkers practice and exemplify the &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/mission-and-values/&quot;&gt;values&lt;/a&gt; we define on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;, ones that drive me as well. How can one &lt;em&gt;_not_&lt;/em&gt; feel welcomed, empowered to excel, and ask for what they need in the onboarding process when they receive Slack messages like this from remote colleagues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Slack screenshot&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/savas-welcome.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Senior Project Manager, Ro Wang, greets me warmly in a private message on Slack.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teammates bring to the table many things, in equal parts tangible and intangible, resulting in a highly productive, respectful, creative, and collaborative environment of humans who work diligently for our clients. I recognized that before I started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my last campaign wrapped up, I knew I would only be fulfilled if I went to work each day for a company that considers the community it operates within, and the unique responsibility it has to contribute (beyond the paid services it came into existence to provide). I was pleased to learn that at Savas Labs, every full-time employee is afforded one day of PTO for community service at an organization of our choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not as significant a factor in my job search, humor in the workplace is definitely a plus. Savas incorporates dad jokes (and other actual humor) into our weekly meetings, so I’ll just leave these here . . .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question: Why did the functional component feel lost?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: Because it didn’t know what &lt;em&gt;state&lt;/em&gt; it was in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:  Why did the child component have such great self-esteem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: Because its parent kept giving it &lt;em&gt;props&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/07/03/savas-brings-on-another-front-end-developer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/07/03/savas-brings-on-another-front-end-developer.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adventures in Estimation: Accuracy and Strategy at Savas Labs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Excellent project management starts with accurate project time estimation and is important for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accurate time estimates assist in setting milestones and managing capacity when project planning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The accuracy (or lack thereof) of your time assessment will inform other’s perception of your reliability and competence as a project manager/company.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time estimates almost always have a significant impact on the financial success of a project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bottom-line-time-estimations-matter-a-lot&quot;&gt;Bottom line: Time estimations matter. A lot.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all too common to underestimate the amount of time needed for a project. Often, this is due to unanticipated challenges, requests for additional features, or unscheduled urgent tasks that occasionally pop up. Even so, estimates remain a key to success in any company—most especially ours, and we strive to keep them accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other things to keep in mind when considering estimates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimates are different from proposals or contracts (read: we estimate in time, not dollars).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimates are not definites.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good estimates take time, discovery, and vetting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimates are ultimately essential to both planning and financial success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Something to be wary of&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90313102/how-to-get-better-at-estimating-your-time&quot;&gt;The Planning Fallacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Planning Fallacy is failing to consider how long it’s taken to complete similar tasks in the past and assuming that we won’t run into any complications that will cause delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are known knowns; there are things we know we know. We also know there are known unknowns; that is to say, we know there are some things we do not know. But there are also unknown unknowns–the ones we don’t know we don’t know.  &lt;span&gt;- Donald Rumsfeld&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a deep dive into our past time estimates (for a presentation at our recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/08/savas-retreat-yo-self.html&quot;&gt;ReTreat Yo Self&lt;/a&gt; team retreat) and comparing to our actual spent time we concluded that as a company:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;calculating&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/calculating.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We like even numbers! (We also love a good &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palindrome&quot;&gt;palindrome&lt;/a&gt;, hence our name).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’ve done a pretty good job, but as always, there is room for improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fight the planning fallacy:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge we (and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/specstimate/why-are-humans-so-bad-at-estimating-4b4290f83716&quot;&gt;the majority&lt;/a&gt;) face is the planning fallacy. So, here are a few suggestions for fighting the planning fallacy (adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90313102/how-to-get-better-at-estimating-your-time&quot;&gt;this helpful article&lt;/a&gt; and my own experience):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data talks.&lt;/strong&gt; And history tends to repeat itself. So use historical data to help make the most accurate estimations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do three estimates.&lt;/strong&gt; Best-case, worst-case, and most likely. Pro tip: assume your initial estimate is “best-case.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check the calendar.&lt;/strong&gt; Take into account the big picture. What other projects will you be working on at these same times? Who will be on vacation and unable to work on the project for a week?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think in “Work Weeks.”&lt;/strong&gt; When we think of how many days we have until a project is due, we often think in actual days not in “work days.” Count only the Monday-Friday days in your estimation. More on &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/ro-wang/&quot;&gt;Ro’s&lt;/a&gt; idea of “Work Weeks” coming soon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FUDGE it!&lt;/strong&gt; Use a fudge ratio:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimate the time it will take to do near-future tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track the actual time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sum the estimates and the actual spent time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Divide the total spent time by the total estimated time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voilà! A fudge ratio! Apply that to future estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phone a friend.&lt;/strong&gt; Call on a coworker or another project manager. When estimating a project they aren’t working on, they are likely to give a far more realistic estimation than you would.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One word: RANGES&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t estimate in perfect numbers, give a range to account for unknowns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Started from the bottom and now…&lt;/strong&gt; Estimate at the low point of your day. That is to say, don’t do estimations when you’ve just had the most delicious lunch, your calendar is free, your inbox is near-empty, and you’re feeling high on life. You’ll be feeling over-optimistic about everything, including your time estimations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revisit&lt;/strong&gt;. After wading into a project, take a look back and revisit initial estimates. You know what they say: “measure twice, cut once.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-we-foster-estimation-success&quot;&gt;How we foster estimation success&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project typically fits into one of two broad categories: one in which we have a high degree of familiarity, and whose scope we understand well, and those we don’t. As discussed, with the former, we use historical records to hone in tightly on the expected efforts. That’s simple. In the latter case, in which the client’s vision is not fully articulated (and this is where we provided the most value), we have learned it’s in both parties best interest to perform a strategy phase upfront. We often call it a discovery, or planning and have found it to be instrumental in getting all stakeholders the same page and reducing risk. Once we’ve elicited all the information we can from conversations with stakeholders and any relevant user testing, we then focus internally. In conjunction with the project manager, the tech lead on a given project is responsible for laying out the plan to execute the project from start to finish. Once the tech lead has produced this detailed document, we have a “designated dissenter” internal meeting in which the goal of one teammate is to pick apart any &lt;em&gt;potentially false&lt;/em&gt; assumptions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/How-does-the-saying-about-assuming-something-go&quot;&gt;you know what they say about those&lt;/a&gt;) made by the tech lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;calculating&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/rbg-dissent.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This direct, constructive feedback is something that I would only consider within a team with a substantial “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/justin-bariso/google-spent-years-studying-effective-teams-this-single-quality-contributed-most-to-their-success.html&quot;&gt;psychological safety&lt;/a&gt;,” which we &lt;a href=&quot;/company/mission-and-values/&quot;&gt;work hard to cultivate and sustain&lt;/a&gt; at Savas. The feedback is a gift that helps avoid potential future pitfalls, but a person will only hear it from someone they trust and know has shared  goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we complete the internal work, we produce one of the most beneficial outputs from the discovery process: a more detailed plan with a more accurate schedule and budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting more accurate time expectations is better for everyone because we create the necessary space—and far less anxiety and pressure—to do better quality work. It creates reliability for the client, for ourselves and our coworkers and generally keeps everything running smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/05/14/adventures-in-estimation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/05/14/adventures-in-estimation.html</guid>
        
        <category>best-practices</category>
        
        <category>business</category>
        
        <category>productivity</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savas Hires a Marketing Coordinator</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, world! (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%22Hello,_World!%22_program&quot;&gt;is that right?&lt;/a&gt;) My name is &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/jordan-nelson/&quot;&gt;Jordan&lt;/a&gt;, and I’m the newest addition to the Savas Team. I’ve joined as the Marketing Coordinator!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be working on—you guessed it—all things marketing! Blog posts (some additional exciting posts are coming very soon), social media (come say hi &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavasLabs?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/savaslabs/?modal=admin_todo_tour&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/company/savas-labs/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and events will be my domain. Plus some other exciting things we may have up our sleeves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Oh boy! This is gonna be good, I can tell. -Dory&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/oh-boy-nemo.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I come from a social media/email marketing background—working in higher education admissions and marketing offices, respectively, as well as the online retail space—and I’m very excited to jump in as part of this very talented Savas Labs team. I’m working to bring you quality content from all of us, keeping you up-to-date on all things Savas and helping get the word out about the great things we do here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned quickly, that here at Savas, music preferences are taken VERY seriously (especially locally in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/durham/&quot;&gt;Durham office&lt;/a&gt;). I was warned that music was a big part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/careers/&quot;&gt;Savas culture (It’s great here—you should come work with us, too!)&lt;/a&gt; and that the “rules” include the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We give &lt;em&gt;all kinds&lt;/em&gt; of music a chance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anyone can &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavasLabs/status/1084825113080578048&quot;&gt;veto any song&lt;/a&gt; at any time, no questions asked&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We always encourage song requests/suggestions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew immediately that my first suggestion was going to make an impression on this music-loving team (and I had learned that &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/chris-russo/&quot;&gt;someone&lt;/a&gt; on the team had an affinity for pop, specifically of the 90’s/2000’s variety).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenge accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggestion: &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/2BgEsaKNfHUdlh97KmvFyo&quot;&gt;2002 by Anne-Marie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends, I’m so glad to report that — much like me taking the position here — it was a great choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;take a bow&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/take-a-bow.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/29/savas-hires-a-marketing-coordinator.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/29/savas-hires-a-marketing-coordinator.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Top 5 Things You Need To Know To Speak Drupal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Oh, hello there. I’m Savas Lab’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/maddy-bishop-van-horn/&quot;&gt;newest project manager&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to being new to Savas, I’m also a Drupal beginner. Before joining Savas, I had experience with several other CMSes (Wordpress, Craft, Joomla!, and Umbraco, in addition to a couple of custom Rails apps.) I didn’t know much about Drupal, but I’d heard enough rumors to be a little afraid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;The learning curve for popular CMSs&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/drupal-learning-curve.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Often shared image, source unknown.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve learned more about Drupal, I’ve come to appreciate that it is an incredibly powerful and flexible CMS and there’s a great community of commercial companies and volunteers who help to build and support it. My coworkers at Savas have helped me overcome the first hurdle in learning to work with Drupal: &lt;strong&gt;understanding Drupal terminology.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we dive in, I’d like to extend a huge thank you to &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/anne-tomasevich/&quot;&gt;Anne&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/chris-russo/&quot;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; for their mentorship and their contributions to this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drupal-terminology&quot;&gt;Drupal Terminology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit it: Drupal terminology is not very intuitive. This article lists the key terms and concepts that I’ve found necessary to get started. I’ll break it into five categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drupal code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taxonomy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Views&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-drupal-code&quot;&gt;1. DRUPAL CODE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Drupal? When we discuss the software package itself, we usually refer to one of the three subsections of code that have specific and distinct purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;drupal-core&quot;&gt;Drupal Core&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The codebase that makes up the basic “core” functionality of Drupal. It’s open source and updated consistently by the Drupal community. When writing this, Drupal 8 was the latest, stable version. The move from Drupal 7 to 8 is an investment, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/2017/11/08/cost-of-drupal-7.html&quot;&gt;it’s worth it&lt;/a&gt; and represents the last time such a substantial effort will be required to upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;modules&quot;&gt;Modules&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A module is a directory of code that extends Drupal features/functionality. Drupal core comes with some modules, and many others are freely available to be downloaded. The Drupal community develops and shares these modules outside of core and they are often referred to as “contrib” (short for contributed). If needed, developers can create &lt;strong&gt;custom&lt;/strong&gt; modules for specific functionality for a given client or project. &lt;em&gt;(Wordpress translation: Modules are like plugins, although they generally require more development knowledge to install and maintain.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;themes&quot;&gt;Themes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Theme is the part of the Drupal codebase that determines how the site and its content are displayed. Theme code includes HTML markup, CSS, JavaScript, and Drupal configuration files. Savas Labs’s clients nearly always require custom theme development, and fortunately Drupal supports an efficient, sophisticated means to build off of or “extend” base themes which reduces the effort to develop and maintain custom themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-content&quot;&gt;2. CONTENT&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content refers to the copy, images, and other media that make up a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;content-type&quot;&gt;Content type&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A collection of fields created and defined by a developer via code or a site builder via the web admin interface. Each field has a set data type, limits, and display specifications. Drupal Core comes with some basic content types, like “article” and “basic page.” Drupal core ships with a couple of basic content types and site builders may define any number of additional content types as the site requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;node&quot;&gt;Node&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A piece of content created by a content editor. Each node has an associated content type. We can display nodes in a variety of ways across the site (we can think of it as a page, although it can be presented in other ways too. These display options are configured by developers by using &lt;strong&gt;views&lt;/strong&gt; - more on that below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;Paragraph&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paragraphs are a powerful feature of Drupal 8 that did not exist in previous versions. Site builders may define Paragraph types, and they can have fields that include text, media, buttons, and more. (I repeat: paragraphs are not just for text.) I like to think of Paragraphs as components that admins can add to a &lt;strong&gt;node&lt;/strong&gt; (which, remember, we can think of as a page). Developers can add &lt;strong&gt;paragraph&lt;/strong&gt; fields to &lt;strong&gt;content types&lt;/strong&gt; to allow content editors to add a variety of &lt;strong&gt;paragraph types&lt;/strong&gt; to a node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- To be honest this seems too complex for beginners - maybe linking to a resource or having an animated GIF inline here to show what a paragraph is would go a long way to help beginners --&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;blocks&quot;&gt;Blocks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blocks are a way to put content in different regions of the site. They can be turned on and off for different pages. Take the example of a sidebar with three distinct pieces of content in it: “latest news”, “relevant content” and “ newsletter signup”. The &lt;strong&gt;region&lt;/strong&gt; would be the sidebar, and the three distinct pieces of content (“latest news”, “relevant content” and “newsletter signup”) would each be a &lt;strong&gt;block&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-taxonomy&quot;&gt;3. TAXONOMY&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxonomy is an essential and powerful part of Drupal. It is a system for classification that Drupal uses to define relationships between content. Think tags and keywords associated with a blog article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;vocabulary&quot;&gt;Vocabulary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vocabulary is a taxonomy type. Like content types, Vocabularies are a defined collection of fields and can have visible pages, but often they do not. Vocabularies are meant to be “tags” for content rather than pieces of content themselves. However, developers can define a vocabulary using any collection of fields, so it is technically possible for a Vocabulary to show up as a page, just uncommon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;term&quot;&gt;Term&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An item within a Vocabulary. You can think of a term as a “tag,” although they can have additional fields, as I mentioned above. &lt;strong&gt;Terms&lt;/strong&gt; are to &lt;strong&gt;Vocabularies&lt;/strong&gt; as &lt;strong&gt;nodes&lt;/strong&gt; are to &lt;strong&gt;content types&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-users&quot;&gt;4. USERS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Drupal’s strengths compared to other CMSes is its highly customizable user permissions and roles. But what does that mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;user&quot;&gt;User&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A user is anyone interacting with the site. Users can be &lt;strong&gt;anonymous&lt;/strong&gt; (any site visitor who is not logged in) or &lt;strong&gt;authenticated&lt;/strong&gt; (a visitor who logged in with an account).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;role&quot;&gt;Role&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A role is a defined type of user with assigned permissions. &lt;strong&gt;Anonymous&lt;/strong&gt; is one role. &lt;strong&gt;Authenticated&lt;/strong&gt; users can be given any number of defined roles, for example: “logged-in user”, “content creator”, and “administrator”. Administrators can create and customize as many roles as they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;permission&quot;&gt;Permission&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permissions are levels of access that can be granted to roles by site administrators. Each &lt;strong&gt;role&lt;/strong&gt; can have a different view and edit permissions (e.g. “view published content”, “administer users”, “create new content”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-views&quot;&gt;5. VIEWS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drupal Views is one of the more powerful features of a Drupal site. It gives site administrators a high level of control and sophistication for grouping and presenting content across the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;views-module&quot;&gt;Views Module&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Views module allows administrators and site designers to create, manage, and display lists of content. Each list managed by the views module is known as a &lt;strong&gt;view&lt;/strong&gt;, and the output of a view is known as a &lt;strong&gt;display&lt;/strong&gt;. Admins can create displays in either block or page form, and a single view may have multiple displays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;view-mode&quot;&gt;View Mode&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;strong&gt;Views module&lt;/strong&gt;, developers can configure each &lt;strong&gt;content type&lt;/strong&gt; to have various &lt;strong&gt;view modes&lt;/strong&gt;. With view modes, admins can output a &lt;strong&gt;node&lt;/strong&gt; in a specific format with a particular set of fields. This format is known as a &lt;strong&gt;display&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a developer may make a “Preview” view mode, which will display a subset of the fields of a given &lt;strong&gt;content type&lt;/strong&gt;. By editing the fields of the node, content editors can change the content displayed in the “Preview” view mode. Another good example of a view mode that a developer may configure is a “search result” view mode, which will define, for each content type, how to display that content on the search page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good news: we made it! I won’t claim that you’re now completely fluent in Drupal, but you should have the foundation to understand and talk about the building blocks of a Drupal site with a developer or site builder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you also new to Drupal? Or are you a Drupal pro? Either way, leave a comment below with your favorite resources.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/22/top-5-things-to-know-to-speak-drupal.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/22/top-5-things-to-know-to-speak-drupal.html</guid>
        
        <category>drupal</category>
        
        <category>drupal8</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savas Brings On (another) Project Manager</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Faithful readers of the Savas Blog, please welcome Maddy to the Savas Team! :wave: We are so excited that she’s here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maddy comes to us from premier Digital Agency, &lt;a href=&quot;https://viget.com&quot;&gt;Viget&lt;/a&gt;, by way of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ewh.org&quot;&gt;Engineering World Health&lt;/a&gt;—a non-profit that uses the skills of students and professionals to improve health care in low-income countries. During her time there, she traveled the globe managing teams of student-engineers working on medical equipment in places like Rwanda, Nepal, and Cambodia—how awesome is that?!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Outdoor meetings together at our airbnb&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/maddy-rwanda-mt-bisoke.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;On the rim of Mt Bisoke in Rwanda (home of the mountain gorillas!)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maddy has project management skills like you wouldn’t believe and we knew she would be a perfect fit for the Savas Labs Team (&lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/careers/&quot;&gt;Think you could be the perfect fit, too? You’re in luck, we’re hiring!&lt;/a&gt;). Her attention to detail, organizational skills, and self-motivated nature a great partner on any project and we’re excited for &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/results/&quot;&gt;current partners&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/services/&quot;&gt;new clients&lt;/a&gt; to get the chance to meet Maddy. We know they will be as impressed as we are!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: Maddy’s very first day on the job wasn’t from &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/contact/&quot;&gt;our Durham, NC office&lt;/a&gt; where she works from, but spent on a plane flying to &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/08/savas-retreat-yo-self.html&quot;&gt;our latest Team Retreat&lt;/a&gt;—in Austin, Texas! Talk about an exciting first day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Outdoor meetings together at our airbnb&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/maddy-austin-retreat.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Hard at work at ReTreat Yo Self.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fun fact about Maddy: She’s a foster dog mom. She’s making an impact in her community by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carolinaadoptabulls.com&quot;&gt;fostering dogs&lt;/a&gt; and loving them well until (and after) they find a fur-ever home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maddy, we are glad you’re here!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/10/savas-welcomes-maddy-bishop-van-horn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/10/savas-welcomes-maddy-bishop-van-horn.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ReTreat Yo' Self: A Savas Labs Team Summit</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Austin, TX March | 2019&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Periodically, the Savas Lab team gathers at a voted-upon location to work in person together, participate in team-building, and prepare for the upcoming year. Most recently we packed our bags, hopped on planes from all over (from as far away as Boston, Rapid City, Reno, and of course, Durham), and touched down in beautiful Austin, TX!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After everyone arrived, we cooked a meal together and settled in our beautiful airbnb before jumping into the two-day, action packed festivities. &lt;a href=&quot;/company/chris-russo&quot;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/company/ben-eckerson/&quot;&gt;Ben&lt;/a&gt; led breakout exercises and team sessions like “Looking Back” – which reflected on Savas Labs as a company and each of our time spent with the company so far (spoiler alert: this was &lt;strong&gt;Maddy’s FIRST DAY&lt;/strong&gt; of work with the team—what a way to start!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Outdoor meetings together at our airbnb&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/outdoor-meeting-austin.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;When you’re somewhere as beautiful as Austin, TX, you hold meetings outside! &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- Anne, I apologize --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;height:100%&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Outdoor project management presentation&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/ro-presenting-pm-austin.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:74%;height:100%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img alt=&quot;Sticky note exercise&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/sticky-notes-austin.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:25%;height:100%;float:right&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Left: Ro leads a project management overview session for the team. Right: sticky-note ideas begin to compile as the team brainstorms the future.&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/company/ro-wang&quot;&gt;Ro&lt;/a&gt; talked about the philosophy and tenants of Project Management at Savas, and how our style as a team is ever-evolving. We ended our team meetings with an exercise and discussion on personal fulfillment and work-life perspective. After a full afternoon of learning we hopped in a couple of Lyfts and headed to a quick dinner at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yelp.com/search?cflt=foodtrucks&amp;amp;find_loc=Rainey+St%2C+Austin%2C+TX+78701&quot;&gt;Rainey Street Food Truck Lot&lt;/a&gt;. Then, off to what was listed on our agenda as “Secret Evening Plans”. All we knew about the secret up until that point was what was written on the schedule: “NOTE: Pack shorts &amp;amp; sandals that can get wet.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out, the secret surprise was an [on-brand] palindromic team kayak excursion to the Congress Avenue Bridge to see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tripsavvy.com/austins-bat-bridge-a-viewing-guide-254880&quot;&gt;Austin’s popular sunset bats&lt;/a&gt;! It was a huge hit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Kayaking on the river/lake&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/ben-and-ro-kayak-austin.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ben and Ro paddle away! Note the matching sweatshirts. The whole team was gifted new Savas swag!
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning some of us fit in some exercise :running_man:, and we all caught up on email and individual work before gathering for &lt;a href=&quot;https://torchystacos.com/menu/&quot;&gt;lunch&lt;/a&gt;. Afternoon team sessions were around the theme of “Looking Forward”—what’s in store for the future of Savas, trends in development from &lt;a href=&quot;/company/anne-tomasevich&quot;&gt;Anne&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/company/dan-murphy&quot;&gt;Dan&lt;/a&gt;, and Oksana, and a look into what marketing plans we have in store for 2019 and beyond (spoiler: that involves &lt;a href=&quot;/company/jordan-nelson&quot;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt;!) . Ideas were pitched, concerns brought to light and addressed, and excitement built! There was an energy at this meeting. An energy of anticipation, excitement, and togetherness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Outdoor meetings together at our airbnb&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/chris-dan-austin-run.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Chris and Dan go on a marathon training run in Austin together.
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We topped off ReTreat Yo Self 2019 with (probably too much) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bufalinapizza.com&quot;&gt;Bufalina Pizza&lt;/a&gt; (if there a such thing as too much pizza?) and fellowship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Departure power posing&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/power-pose-austin.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Do you think everyone is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_posing&quot;&gt;power posing&lt;/a&gt; on purpose?
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s to the future of Savas Labs! We are excited &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/careers/&quot;&gt;to be growing (come work with us!)&lt;/a&gt;, taking on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DukeGHI/status/1113538130706145280&quot;&gt;new&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/results/&quot;&gt;impactful projects&lt;/a&gt;, and have the opportunity to work together each day. Until next time, Austin!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/08/savas-retreat-yo-self.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/08/savas-retreat-yo-self.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savas Claus™: The inaugural holiday tradition</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;‘Tis the season of :gift: giving. Now that we’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/12/11/savas-welcomes-ben-eckerson-coo.html&quot;&gt;brought Ben on&lt;/a&gt;, along with him has followed ample holiday cheer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;padding:76.12% 0 0 0;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe class=&quot;m0&quot; src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/24452526?autoplay=1&amp;amp;title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/api/player.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ben was “Snowglobe Boy” for former employer ad agency &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckinney.com/&quot;&gt;Mckinney&lt;/a&gt; in December 2007 receiving over 100 million media impressions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben suggested — and we swiftly agreed to — our first annual Savas Claus™: the name we chose for our year-end holiday gift giving tradition. Oft referred to as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_Santa&quot;&gt;Secret Santa&lt;/a&gt;, a group of people buys gifts for one another while keeping the giver and receivers anonymous until the big reveal. It’s a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, to randomly assign gift receivers to their respective givers, you write everyone’s name down on paper, put the names into a hat, and each person blindly picks a name for whom they get a gift. However, this analog approach has &lt;em&gt;one major flaw&lt;/em&gt;: one can easily end up with himself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://media1.tenor.com/images/fe6a574d37f0b0189d412bb11e719906/tenor.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Kevin from the Office gets himself for Secret Santa&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-challenges&quot;&gt;The challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we knew we had ahead of us one of &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/bliki/TwoHardThings.html&quot;&gt;the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; hard problems in computer science&lt;/a&gt;: cache-invalidation, off-by-one errors, and &lt;strong&gt;naming things&lt;/strong&gt;. Giving the naming task the gravity it deserved, we put it to a poll. Savas Claus™ prevailed by a narrow margin over Secret Savas (its main critique: being too close to “secret service”). Given the aforementioned self-selection consideration (“the Kevin problem”) and the fact that our team is distributed, we went for a digital solution. After all, we &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; web engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-approach&quot;&gt;The approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Slack is so deeply ingrained in our day-to-day, we looked for a solution there first. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.slack.com/apps/A0E7EFUB1-secret-santa&quot;&gt;Secret Santa Slack app does exist&lt;/a&gt;, yet it didn’t afford us the flexibility and panache we were going for — plus it’s way more fun to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/savaslabs/savas-slack-tools/pull/5&quot;&gt;make your own&lt;/a&gt;! So we (well Chris) got in some weekend time to build a simple Slack app that would serve our needs during our weekly Monday morning team-wide status call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use tools on a near-daily basis that randomize the order of our team, for purposes like who gets to choose the lunch spot each week when we go out, or to randomize the order we speak during our weekly status call. So, adding the Savas Claus™ functionality was a natural extension to what we already had. The app creates a random order of the team (the “givers”), generates a second randomly ordered list of the team (“the receivers”) and pairs them with each other. If there are any repeats among the two lists in the same slot, the app automatically regenerates the second list and will repeat until the lists share no one in the same slot, and therefore receivers can safely be assigned to givers. With the lists vetted, the Slack app privately messages each giver notifying them of their respective recipient. The message looks &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/savas-claus-chris-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chris's resulting Savas Claus private message&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NB: the exclamation point was meant to be a subtly hidden link, an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Easter_egg_(media)&quot;&gt;:rabbit: :egg: easter egg&lt;/a&gt; if you will, but it seems Slack sensed it was the wrong time of year for such shenanigans and sabotaged the surprise unfurling the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B6jCMaiTqG0&quot;&gt;office reference&lt;/a&gt; for all to see plainly. You win some and you lose some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-results-santa-christmas_tree-gift-gift_heart&quot;&gt;The results :santa: :christmas_tree: :gift: :gift_heart:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team is currently prepping and/or shipping their gifts before our “unwrapping” virtual party/social of sorts in a couple days. No doubt we’ll use our “Savas Shuffle” Slackbot to determine the order for who will open their gifts first. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/savaslabs&quot;&gt;Follow us on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and we’ll share the real results (the gifts!) from our first annual Savas Claus™.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2018/12/17/savas-claus.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2018/12/17/savas-claus.html</guid>
        
        <category>open-source</category>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcoming Ben Eckerson as COO of Savas Labs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For a little over a month now, &lt;a href=&quot;/company/ben-eckerson&quot;&gt;Ben Eckerson&lt;/a&gt; has been working hard to make an impact as Savas Labs’ new and first Chief Operating Officer. Ben joins us after six years at premier digital agency &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.viget.com/&quot;&gt;Viget&lt;/a&gt;, where he led business development and experimental IoT efforts for their Durham office (a couple blocks away from us in downtown Durham). Prior to Viget, Ben spent six years at creative New York/Durham agency &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckinney.com/&quot;&gt;Mckinney&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s Ben dressed up in his finest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Ben rocking his Spiderman sweater in kindergarten&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/ben-as-a-child.png&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ben dove right in sharing this kindergarten school photo with the team.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-ben-is-doing-at-savas-labs&quot;&gt;What Ben is doing at Savas Labs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With well over a decade in leadership roles in digital agencies, Ben will help to improve our operations to enhance the value we’re providing to our partners. He’ll also help get the exemplary work we do here at Savas out in the world better. Known for his knack for turning creative visions into reality, Ben will be the first person a new organization has a conversation with about how we can help them achieve their hopes and dreams or the first phone chat of a &lt;a href=&quot;/careers&quot;&gt;prospective job candidate&lt;/a&gt;. Beyond his official duties, Ben is a high-energy, team player who seeks to foster a fun and healthy culture with his new work family and we’re seeing that impact already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-that-have-changed-since-bens-start&quot;&gt;Things that have changed since Ben’s start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’ve transitioned our internal team planning and scheduling efforts to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.getharvest.com/forecast&quot;&gt;Harvest’s forecast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’ve improved our retrospective process and documentation as well as our organization of project files in our Google Drive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’ve had to up our Slack subscription to keep pace with Ben’s uncanny ability to find the perfect GIF (or create a new custom emoji) for any conversation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’ve implemented a &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/12/17/savas-claus.html&quot;&gt;Secret Santa&lt;/a&gt; tradition in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B6jCMaiTqG0&quot;&gt;the office&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’ve instituted (and started planning) semi-annual retreats to bring together the full distributed team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Map of country and team central meeting location&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/retreat-map.png&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;One of Ben's nominations for our retreat is Paris (Illinois).&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;helping-to-make-savas-labs-more-social&quot;&gt;Helping to make Savas Labs more social&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben has &lt;em&gt;gently&lt;/em&gt; recommended that we more frequently share how special what we’ve created at Savas Labs is – hence my writing of this blog post &lt;del&gt;that he made me write&lt;/del&gt; about him. He also noted that the team has been so busy there was little time for engagement on social media. For fears he was beginning to detect some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bewKPi9gdT4&quot;&gt;early onset grumpiness&lt;/a&gt;, Ben has taken swift action to combat things before it’s too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;jekyll-twitter-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;We are thrilled to announce (and welcome) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/beneckerson?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@beneckerson&lt;/a&gt; as our new COO! Welcome to the Savas team, Ben! We&amp;#39;re so excited to have you!&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Savas Labs (@SavasLabs) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavasLabs/status/1059906716224110597?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;November 6, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/embed/feed/update/urn:li:share:6463430533543194624&quot; height=&quot;483&quot; width=&quot;504&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome Ben; we’re grateful to have you! :handshake:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned :radio: for more hiring announcements coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2018/12/11/savas-welcomes-ben-eckerson-coo.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2018/12/11/savas-welcomes-ben-eckerson-coo.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to transition your website from HTTP to HTTPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part two of a two-part series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/26/why-you-need-https.html&quot;&gt;part one&lt;/a&gt;, we cogently convinced you that regardless of what your organization does and what functionality your website has, it is in your best interest to serve your website securely over HTTPS exclusively. Here we provide some guidance as to how to make the move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-transition-to-https&quot;&gt;How to transition to HTTPS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fully transition to HTTPS from HTTP means to serve your website HTML and assets exclusively over HTTPS. This requires a few basic things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A digital certificate from a certificate authority (CA)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proper installation of the certificate on your website’s server&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensuring all assets served from your website are served over HTTPS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break these down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;acquire-a-digital-certificate&quot;&gt;Acquire a digital certificate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As briefly discussed in &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/26/why-you-need-https.html&quot;&gt;part one&lt;/a&gt;, to implement HTTPS for your website you must procure a digital certificate from a certificate authority. Just like domain name registrars lease domain names, CAs lease digital certificates for a set time period. Each certificate has a public and private component. The public component is freely shared and allows browsers to recognize that a “trusted” CA was the one to distribute the certificate. It is also used to encrypt data transmitted from the browser. The private complement is only shared with the purchaser of the certificate, and can uniquely decrypt data encrypted by the public key. CAs use various methods through email or DNS to “prove” that the person who purchased the certificate is a rightful administrator of the domain for which they purchased it. Once you’ve received the private key associated with the certificate, you’ll need to install it on your server. Annual certificate costs can be as much as $1,000 or as little as nothing. More on that in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;install-the-certificate&quot;&gt;Install the certificate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/assets/img/blog/install-https-analogy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lots of wires&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing an HTTPS certificate manually on a server is not a trivial engineering task. We &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/26/why-you-need-https.html#what-authentication-does-for-you&quot;&gt;explain this at a high-level in part one&lt;/a&gt;. It  requires expertise from someone who is experienced and comfortable administering servers. There are many different installation methods unique to each permutation of server software and hosting platform, so I won’t expend any real estate here attempting to lay it out. If you have to do a manual installation, it’s best to search your hosting provider’s documentation. However, depending on the complexity of your website architecture, there are ways to ease this process. Some hosting platforms have tools that substantially simplify the installation process. More on &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; in a moment as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;serve-all-resources-over-https-avoid-mixed-content&quot;&gt;Serve all resources over HTTPS: avoid mixed content&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve installed your certificate, it’s time to ensure all assets served from your pages are served over HTTPS. Naturally, this entire process should be completed in a staging environment before making the switch to your production environment. Completing a full transition to HTTPS requires attention to detail and diligence. “Mixed content”, or serving assets from a page over both HTTP &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; HTTPS, can be both tedious and insidious to rectify. The longer your site has been around, the more content there is and the more historic hands have been in the pot of content creation, the more work there will be to make the switch. Depending on your platform (CMS or otherwise) and how it was designed, there may be many avenues for different stakeholders to have included assets within a page over time. Developers, site admins, and content editors usually have the ability to add assets to a page. If any assets start with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://&lt;/code&gt;, they’ll need to be updated to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://&lt;/code&gt; to prevent mixed content warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have recently helped a client who has been publishing articles at a high cadence for over 10 years with many different stakeholders over that period. Practices weren’t consistent and uncovering all the ways in which HTTP resources were served from the page was a substantial undertaking. Therefore, be prepared for a time investment here – there may be many areas to audit to ensure all assets from all your pages are being served over HTTPS. Some common ways mixed content HTTP assets are served from a site whose HTML is served over HTTPS are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hard-coding a resource: e.g. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://www.example.com/img/insecure-image.jpg&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using a 3rd-party library or ad network reference: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://www.example.com/js/analytics.js&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This is common for libraries that haven’t been updated in a while. Most all of them now serve the same assets over the same path securely with HTTPS.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paulirish.com/2010/the-protocol-relative-url/&quot;&gt;practices that were previously encouraged by Paul Irish&lt;/a&gt;, a leading web architect for the Google Chrome team, may have contributed to your mixed content problem, so don’t feel bad. Just know, there will likely be work to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-risk-of-mixed-content&quot;&gt;The risk of mixed content&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These “not secure” bits of mixed-content &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/security/prevent-mixed-content/what-is-mixed-content#mixed_content_weakens_https&quot;&gt;expose the same risk&lt;/a&gt; that your HTML does when served over HTTP, so browsers rightfully show the user that the experience on your site is “not secure”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mixed content is categorized in two ways: active and passive. An asset that can contribute to passive mixed content would be an image; it doesn’t interact with the page but is merely presented on the page. An example that can be an active asset of mixed content is a javascript file or stylesheet since its purpose is to manipulate the page. Passive mixed content, albeit categorically less severe than active, still exposes opportunities for an attacker to learn a lot about an individual’s browsing patterns and even trick them into taking different actions than they intend to on the page. Therefore passive mixed content still constitutes enough of a threat for the browser to issue a warning display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/assets/img/blog/mixed-content-errors.png&quot; alt=&quot;mixed content browser errors&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of an active asset that is compromised, if it were a javascript file, an attacker can take full control of the page and any interaction you may have with it like entering passwords, or credit card information. The mechanism behind this is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/security/prevent-mixed-content/what-is-mixed-content#mixed_content_types_security_threats_associated&quot;&gt;somewhat sophisticated man-in-the-middle attack&lt;/a&gt;, but suffice it to say, if the browser recognizes the vulnerability, the best scenario is the &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/26/why-you-need-https.html#https-improves-credibility-and-ux&quot;&gt;poor user experience we discussed in part one&lt;/a&gt;, the worst is total data compromise. Your audience, and by association your organization, will be seeing red.
&lt;br /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/assets/img/blog/misconfigured-https.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chrome misconfigured HTTPS&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-good-news-about-moving-to-https&quot;&gt;The good news about moving to HTTPS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring your website serves assets exclusively over HTTPS is not as hard as it used to be, and is getting easier by the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;there-are-free-digital-certificates&quot;&gt;There are free digital certificates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no such thing as a free lunch, but a free certificate from a reputable CA? It would seem so. People are just giving them away these days… Seriously, many years in the making since its founding by two Mozilla employees in 2012, the Let’s Encrypt project has vowed to make the web a secure space and has successfully endeavored to become a trusted CA that literally does not charge for the certificates they provide. They have shorter lease cycles of 60 to 90 days, but they also offer tooling around automating the process of reinstalling newly provided certificates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;there-are-easier-and-cheaper-ways-to-install-certificates&quot;&gt;There are easier and cheaper ways to install certificates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of the aforementioned free certificate, many platform-as-a-service (PaaS) hosting options have incorporated low cost or free installation of certificates through their hosting platform sometimes as easily as a few clicks. Let’s Encrypt has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.letsencrypt.org/t/web-hosting-who-support-lets-encrypt/6920&quot;&gt;adopted across a broad range of website hosting providers&lt;/a&gt; like Squarespace, GitHub Pages, Dreamhost, all of which we use alongside many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many of our Drupal partners, we prefer to use a platform as a service (PaaS) hosting option like Pantheon, Acquia, or Platform.sh. Both &lt;a href=&quot;https://pantheon.io/features/managed-https&quot;&gt;Pantheon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://platform.sh/blog/free-ssl-certificates-for-every-project-every-environment&quot;&gt;Platform.sh&lt;/a&gt; now provide a free HTTPS upgrade for all hosting plans; Acquia Cloud, another popular Drupal PaaS, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://redfinsolutions.com/blog/installing-free-lets-encrypt-ssl-certificates-acquia#comment-3290247800&quot;&gt;still a bit behind in this regard&lt;/a&gt;. We have found that the efficiency gains of spending less time in server administration translates to more value to our clients, empowering additional effort for the strategy, design, and development for which they hired us. In addition to efficiency, the reliability and consistency provided by finely tuned PaaS offerings are, in most cases, superior to manual installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example of the evolution of hosting platforms maturing into the HTTPS everywhere world is our own Jekyll-based site, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tag/jekyll&quot;&gt;which we’ve written about&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fldrupal.camp/sessions/sessions-drupal-island/strange-case-dr-jekyll-and-mr-drupal&quot;&gt;presented on before&lt;/a&gt;. We first set up HTTPS over GitHub pages using CloudFlare guided by &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.cloudflare.com/secure-and-fast-github-pages-with-cloudflare/&quot;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt; since we found it necessary to serve our site over HTTPS. However, about a year later &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.github.com/2018-05-01-github-pages-custom-domains-https/&quot;&gt;GitHub announced they would provide HTTPS support for GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;jekyll-twitter-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Today, custom domains on GitHub Pages are gaining support for HTTPS via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/letsencrypt?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@letsencrypt&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s another step towards making the web more secure for everyone. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/MbB7Jjd3EE&quot;&gt;https://t.co/MbB7Jjd3EE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; GitHub (@github) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/github/status/991366832421523456?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 1, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we had previously implemented &lt;a href=&quot;https://pantheon.io/blog/using-cloudflare-run-pantheon-sites-under-https-free&quot;&gt;Pantheon’s workaround&lt;/a&gt; to make HTTPS on all of their tiers accessible to our clients on their hosting platform. Then &lt;a href=&quot;https://pantheon.io/blog/pantheon-launches-global-cdn-automated-https-all-sites&quot;&gt;they announced HTTPS for all sites&lt;/a&gt;. We’re thankful both have gotten easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;there-are-tools-to-help-with-the-transition-to-https&quot;&gt;There are tools to help with the transition to HTTPS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through its powerful Lighthouse suite, Google has &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/web/tools/lighthouse/audits/mixed-content&quot;&gt;a tool to help audit and fix mixed content issues&lt;/a&gt;. Given the aforementioned tedium and potential difficulty of tracking down all the ways in which people have historically added content to your site, this can be an invaluable time saver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also use tools like Qualys SSL Labs to verify the quality of your HTTPS installation. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ssllabs.com/ssltest/analyze.html?d=savaslabs.com&amp;amp;latest&quot;&gt;how our site stacks up&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wrap-up&quot;&gt;Wrap-up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the much greater ease at which many modern hosting platforms allow for HTTPS, the biggest barrier, primarily a matter of effort, is to clean up your content and make sure all assets are served over HTTPS from all pages within your website. So, if you haven’t already, start the transition now! &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;Contact us&lt;/a&gt; over the phone or email if you need assistance and feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;#js-comments&quot;&gt;comment below&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2018/08/01/how-to-move-to-https.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2018/08/01/how-to-move-to-https.html</guid>
        
        <category>marketing</category>
        
        <category>user-experience</category>
        
        <category>best-practices</category>
        
        <category>performance</category>
        
        <category>drupal</category>
        
        <category>drupal-planet</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why your website needs HTTPS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is part one of a &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/08/01/how-to-move-to-https.html&quot;&gt;two-part series&lt;/a&gt; on transitioning to HTTPS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time, major internet players have advocated for a ubiquitous, secure internet, touting the myriad benefits for all users and service providers of “HTTPS everywhere”. The most prominent and steadfast among them is Google. In the next week, continuing a multi-year effort to shepherd more traffic to the secure web, Google will make perhaps its boldest move to date which will negatively impact all organizations not securely serving their website over HTTPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://security.googleblog.com/2018/02/a-secure-web-is-here-to-stay.html&quot;&gt;Google Security Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Beginning in July 2018 with the release of Chrome 68, Chrome will mark all HTTP sites as “not secure”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/assets/img/blog/chrome-68-not-secure.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chrome insecure message for HTTP&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Google blog &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the ambiguous “in July 2018”, with no clearly communicated release date for Chrome 68, it’s wise to err on the side of caution and assume it will roll out on the 1st. We have readied our partners with this expectation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this mean for your organization if your site is not served over HTTPS? In short, it’s time to make the move. Let’s dig in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-https&quot;&gt;What is HTTPS?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HTTP, or &lt;strong&gt;H&lt;/strong&gt;yper&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;ext &lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt;ransfer &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;rotocol, is the internet technology used to communicate between your web browser and the servers that the websites you visit are on. HTTPS is the secure version (s for secure) which is served over TLS: Transport Layer Security. What these technical acronyms equate to are tools for internet communication that verify you’re communicating with who you think you are, in the way you intended to, in a format that only the intended recipient can understand. We’ll touch on the specifics in a moment and why they’re important. Put simply, HTTPS enables secure internet communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-secure-browsing-matters&quot;&gt;Why secure browsing matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving aside the technical details for a moment and taking a broader view than communication protocols reveals more nuanced benefits your organization receives by communicating securely with its audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;https-improves-seo&quot;&gt;HTTPS improves SEO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Google accounts for 75-90% of global search queries (&lt;a href=&quot;https://netmarketshare.com/search-engine-market-share.aspx?options=%7B%22filter%22%3A%7B%22%24and%22%3A%5B%7B%22deviceType%22%3A%7B%22%24in%22%3A%5B%22Desktop%2Flaptop%22%5D%7D%7D%5D%7D%2C%22dateLabel%22%3A%22Trend%22%2C%22attributes%22%3A%22share%22%2C%22group%22%3A%22searchEngine%22%2C%22sort%22%3A%7B%22share%22%3A-1%7D%2C%22id%22%3A%22searchEnginesDesktop%22%2C%22dateInterval%22%3A%22Monthly%22%2C%22dateStart%22%3A%222017-06%22%2C%22dateEnd%22%3A%222018-05%22%2C%22segments%22%3A%22-1000%22%7D&quot;&gt;depending&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/267161/market-share-of-search-engines-in-the-united-states/&quot;&gt;on&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smartinsights.com/search-engine-marketing/search-engine-statistics/&quot;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://gs.statcounter.com/search-engine-market-share&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;) SEO is understandably often synonymous with optimizing for Google. Given their market domination, competitors are taking queues from Google and in most cases it’s safe to assume what’s good for SEO in Google is good for optimizing competing search engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2014, &lt;a href=&quot;https://webmasters.googleblog.com/2014/08/https-as-ranking-signal.html&quot;&gt;Google announced on their blog&lt;/a&gt; that they would begin to favorably rank sites who used HTTPS over HTTP. It’s already been nearly four years since we’ve known HTTPS to be advantageous for SEO. Since then, Google has consistently advocated the concept of HTTPS ubiquity, frequently writing about it in blog posts and speaking about it at conferences. The extent to which serving your site over HTTPS improves your SEO is not cut and dry and can vary slightly depending on industry. However, the trend toward favoring HTTPS is well under way and the scales are tipped irreversibly at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;https-improves-credibility-and-ux&quot;&gt;HTTPS improves credibility and UX&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a user has arrived at your site, their perceptions may be largely shaped by whether the site is served over HTTP or HTTPS. The user experience when interacting with a site being served over HTTPS is demonstrably better. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semrush.com/blog/https-just-a-google-ranking-signal/#header2&quot;&gt;SEMrush summarizes well&lt;/a&gt; what the data clearly indicate; people care a great deal about security on the web. A couple highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/467656/us-online-shopping-concerns/&quot;&gt;second highest concern for online shoppers was security&lt;/a&gt;. The first was shipping being too expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/339735/crime-worries-in-the-united-states/&quot;&gt;Crimes Americans worried about the most in 2016&lt;/a&gt;: #2 having credit card stolen (69%), and #3 having web identity compromised (64%).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You never get a second chance to make a first impression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With engaging a participant of your target audience, you have precious few moments to instill a sense of credibility with them. This is certainly true of the first time a user interacts with your site, but is also true for returning users. You have to earn your reputation every day, and it can be lost quickly. We know credibility decisions are &lt;a href=&quot;http://credibility.stanford.edu/guidelines/index.html&quot;&gt;highly influenced by design choices&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01449290500330448&quot;&gt;are made in well under one second&lt;/a&gt;. Combining these two insights, with the visual updates Chrome is making to highlight the security of a user’s connection to your site, drawing the user’s attention to a warning in the URL bar translates to a potentially costly loss in credibility. Unfortunately it’s the sort of thing that users won’t notice unless there’s a problem, and per the referenced cliché, at that point it may be too late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;browsers-drawing-attention-to-insecure-http&quot;&gt;Browsers drawing attention to insecure HTTP&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like search, browser usage patterns have evolved over the last five years to heavily favor Google Chrome. Therefore, what Google does carries tremendous weight internet-wide. Current estimations of browser usage put Chrome between 55% and 60% of the market (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usage_share_of_web_browsers&quot;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gs.statcounter.com/browser-market-share&quot;&gt;depending&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://netmarketshare.com/browser-market-share.aspx&quot;&gt;on&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3counter.com/trends&quot;&gt;sources&lt;/a&gt;). Firefox has followed suit with Chrome as far as HTTP security alerts go, and there’s no indication we should expect this to change. So it’s safe to assume a combined 60-75% of the market is represented by Chrome’s updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;google-chrome-http-warning-roll-out&quot;&gt;Google Chrome HTTP warning roll out&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google (and closely mirroring behind, Firefox) has been getting more stringent in their display of the security implications of a site served over HTTP (in addition to sites misconfigured over HTTPS). They’ve shared details on the six-step roll out on &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.chromium.org/2018/05/evolving-chromes-security-indicators.html&quot;&gt;their general blog&lt;/a&gt; as well as on a more technical, granular level on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chromium.org/Home/chromium-security/marking-http-as-non-secure&quot;&gt;Chrome browser blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January 2017, they began marking any site that collects a password field or credit card information, served over HTTP as subtly (grey text) not secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/assets/img/blog/jan-2017-http-not-secure.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chrome insecure message for HTTP&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Laravel News&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, in October 2017, they tightened things up so that a site that collected &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; form information over HTTP, would have the same “not secure” messaging. They added the more action-based aspect of showing the warning on the URL bar &lt;em&gt;when a user entered data into a form&lt;/em&gt;. This is an especially obtrusive experience on mobile due to space constraints, which more deeply engages the user cognitively as to exactly what is unsafe about how they’re interacting with the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/assets/img/blog/oct-2017-http-insecure.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Chrome insecure message for HTTP&quot; class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Google blog &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, in July 2018, all HTTP sites will be marked as not secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2018, secure sites will be marked more neutrally, removing the green secure lock by default connoting a continuing expectation that HTTPS is the norm and no longer special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/assets/img/blog/sep-2018-neutral-https.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chrome insecure message for HTTP&quot; class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Google blog &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2018, any HTTP site that accepts any form fields will show affirmatively not secure with a &lt;span style=&quot;color:#cc0000&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;bold red label&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, much like a misconfigured HTTPS site does now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/assets/img/blog/oct-2018-http-affirmative-insecure.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Chrome insecure message for HTTP&quot; class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; Google blog &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though they haven’t yet announced a date, Google intends to show affirmatively not secure for all HTTP sites. The drive is clearly to establish the norm that all the web traffic should be served over HTTPS and that outdated HTTP is not to be trusted. This is a pretty strong message that if Google has their way (which they usually do) HTTPS will inevitably be virtually mandatory. And inevitably in internet years, may be right around the corner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;https-vastly-improves-security-for-you-and-your-users&quot;&gt;HTTPS vastly improves security for you and your users&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to the technical, as mentioned previously, HTTPS helps secure communication in three basic ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authentication&lt;/strong&gt; “you’re communicating with who you think you are”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data integrity&lt;/strong&gt; “in the way you intended to”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encryption&lt;/strong&gt;: “in a format that only the intended recipient can understand”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-authentication-does-for-you&quot;&gt;What authentication does for you&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for the browser to recognize and evaluate an HTTPS certificate, it must be verified by a trusted certificate authority (CA). There are a limited amount of CAs who are entrusted to distribute HTTPS certificates. Through &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public-key_cryptography&quot;&gt;public-key cryptography&lt;/a&gt;, a fairly complex but interesting topic, through inherent trust in the CA who has provided the HTTPS certificate for a given site, the browser can verify any site visitor is positively communicating with the expected entity with no way of anyone else posing as that entity. No such verification is possible over HTTP and it’s fairly simple to imagine what identify theft would be possible if you were communicating with a different website than you appeared to be. In the event any of the major browsers cannot validate the expected certificate, they will show a strong, usually red warning that you may not be communicating with the expected website, and strongly encourage you to reconsider interacting at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/assets/img/blog/misconfigured-https.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chrome misconfigured HTTPS&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the authentication gives your users the confidence you are who you say you are, which is important when you’re engaging with them in any way whether they’re providing an email, credit card or simply reading articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-data-integrity-helps-you&quot;&gt;How data integrity helps you&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring perfect preservation of communication over the internet is another guarantee HTTPS provides. When a user communicates with a website over HTTPS, the browser takes the input of that communication and using a one-way hashing function creates a unique “message digest”: a concise, alphanumeric string. The digest may only be reliably recreated by running the exact same input through the same hash algorithm irrespective of where and when this is done. For each request the user makes to the website, the browser passes a message digest alongside it and the server then runs the input it receives from the request through the hash algorithm to verify it matches the browser-sent digest. Since it is nearly computationally impossible to reverse engineer these hash functions, if the digests match, it proves the message was not altered in transit. Again, no such data integrity preservation is possible over HTTP, and there is therefore no way to tell if a message has been altered en route to the server from the browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-encryption-does-for-you&quot;&gt;What encryption does for you&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communicating over an unencrypted HTTP connection allows for some easily exploitable security risks in the case of authentication to a site. To demonstrate how easy it can be to take over someone’s account on an HTTP connection, a tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Firesheep&quot;&gt;Firesheep&lt;/a&gt; was developed and openly released in mid 2010. Major social media platforms  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcworld.com/article/209333/how_to_hijack_facebook_using_firesheep.html&quot;&gt;Facebook and Twitter were both susceptible&lt;/a&gt; to this exploit for some time after Firesheep was released. The identity theft is carried out through a means called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Session_hijacking&quot;&gt;session hijacking&lt;/a&gt;. With Firesheep installed, a few clicks could log you in as another user who was browsing over WiFi nearby on any HTTP website. This form of session hijacking is possible when the authentication cookies, small identifying pieces of information that live in your browser while you’re logged into a site, are transmitted to the server  on each request over HTTP. Over WiFi these messages are broadcasted into the air in plain text, and can be picked up by anyone listening. HTTPS prevents this since the communication is encrypted and unintelligible to eavesdroppers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example of a CMS like Drupal or any other system in which there is a login, if an administrator with elevated site permissions is logged in over HTTP, they’re subject to the same risk if that traffic is monitored or “sniffed” at any point along its path from the browser to the server. This is especially easy over WiFi but is not relegated to only WiFi. The cookies are sent to the server upon every request, regardless of whether or not the user entered their password during the active session or not. Depending on the admin’s privileges, this access can be easily escalated to complete control of the website. Encryption is a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;https-is-required-for-the-modern-web&quot;&gt;HTTPS is required for the modern web&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more promising developments of the last few years, is the pervasiveness and effectiveness of Progressive Web Apps (PWAs). PWAs is the name coined for a set of technologies that provide a feature-set for mobile browsing akin to native applications, yet is entirely served through the web browser. PWAs require all communication to be done over HTTPS. Some of the possibilities with PWAs that were previously relegated to native applications only are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing content and services based on the user’s location data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing interaction with the user’s camera and microphone within the browsing experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sending push notifications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serving off-line content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t taking advantage of any of these features that are possible through PWAs, it’s something your organization should strongly consider to further engage users. Before the ambitions to be on feature parity with native applications are fully borne-out, PWAs will continue to evolve the power of layering deeper engagement with users on top of your existing mobile experience with minimal effort. PWAs simply do not work over HTTP. HTTPS is required to open the door to their possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;barriers-to-https-have-been-lifted&quot;&gt;Barriers to HTTPS have been lifted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, considering a move to HTTPS has been held back by some valid concerns for webmasters whose job it was to select where and how their websites were hosted. A few of the fundamental apprehensions could be categorized as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No perceived benefit.&lt;/strong&gt; People often assumed if they weren’t collecting financial or personal information, it wasn’t necessary. We’ve covered why holding this belief in 2018 is a misconception. Savas Labs made the move in July 2017 to serve exclusively over HTTPS for our &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tag/jekyll/&quot;&gt;statically-generated Jekyll website&lt;/a&gt; even though at the time we had no forms or logins.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance costs.&lt;/strong&gt; We know reducing latency is crucial for optimizing conversions and HTTPS does require additional communication and computation. However, with the broad adoption of the HTTP/2 protocol over the last few years, HTTPS now &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.httpvshttps.com/&quot;&gt;usually outperforms HTTP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial costs.&lt;/strong&gt; HTTPS was too complex and costly to implement for some. Large strides have been made across many hosting providers who now bundle HTTPS into their hosting offerings by default, often at no additional cost. &lt;a href=&quot;https://letsencrypt.org/&quot;&gt;Let’s Encrypt&lt;/a&gt;, a relatively new and novel certificate authority, first began offering free certificates (which they still do) and then made it easy to automatically renew those certificates, helping to ease the burden and cost of implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cover each of these in more detail in &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/08/01/how-to-move-to-https.html&quot;&gt;part two&lt;/a&gt; that will help guide you on how to make the move to HTTPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To revisit Google’s announcement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Beginning in July 2018 with the release of Chrome 68, Chrome will mark all HTTP sites as “not secure”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interpreting that and providing our perspective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You’re not part of the modern web unless you’re exclusively using HTTPS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bold, if slightly controversial statement, but for ambitious organizations like the folks we’re fortunate enough to work with each day, HTTPS-only is the standard in mid 2018 and beyond. Given the benefits, the lifted previous barriers, and the opportunity for the future, very few organization have a good reason not to exclusively serve their sites over HTTPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have we convinced you yet? Great! Read &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/08/01/how-to-move-to-https.html&quot;&gt;part two&lt;/a&gt; for some assistance on how to make the move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;additional-resources&quot;&gt;Additional resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cBhZ6S0PFCY&quot;&gt;Google I/O 2014: “HTTPS Everywhere”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e6DUrH56g14&quot;&gt;Progressive Web App Summit 2016: Mythbusting HTTPS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://conversionxl.com/blog/first-impressions-matter-the-importance-of-great-visual-design&quot;&gt;First Impressions Matter: The Importance of Great Visual Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.httpvshttps.com/&quot;&gt;A demonstration of speed benefits of HTTP/2 via HTTPS over HTTP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2018/06/26/why-you-need-https.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2018/06/26/why-you-need-https.html</guid>
        
        <category>marketing</category>
        
        <category>user-experience</category>
        
        <category>best-practices</category>
        
        <category>performance</category>
        
        <category>drupal</category>
        
        <category>drupal-planet</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
