<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Savas Labs</title>
    <description>We design digital products that users love
</description>
    <link>https://savaslabs.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://savaslabs.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 19:01:49 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 19:01:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Working with Storybook and Drupal (Part 1)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, the team at Savas Labs decided to embark on integrating component libraries into our projects. Component libraries are becoming more and more commonplace in front-end development, particularly with frameworks like React and Vue. However, you don’t need to be using a front-end framework to leverage the benefits of a component library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-a-component-library&quot;&gt;What’s a Component Library?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A component library is a repository of reusable building blocks for your website. Think of some of the items that appear on a website over and over again. There are small items (like form elements) and bigger ones (like an image carousel). These are components. For some examples, head over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://getbootstrap.com/docs/3.4/components/&quot;&gt;Bootstrap’s documentation&lt;/a&gt;, where they lay out some of the many reusable components available with the framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Component-based design goes hand in hand with the practice of &lt;a href=&quot;http://bradfrost.com/blog/post/atomic-web-design/&quot;&gt;atomic design&lt;/a&gt;. This methodology breaks down elements into five categories: Atoms, Molecules, Organisms, Templates, and Pages. Atoms are the smallest parts of your site. Atoms build molecules, molecules build organisms, etc. I highly recommend visiting the link and learning more about this methodology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-are-we-using-a-component-library&quot;&gt;Why Are We Using a Component Library?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, we want to be more efficient. One of the many draws of using a component library here at Savas is the ability for front-end developers to start building out pieces of a project before our back-end team has the Drupal site up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be familiar with the common coding practice DRY (Don’t Repeat Yourself). Leveraging a component library in our projects allows us to make that practice a reality. We can build one component to be flexible enough for a variety of use cases (more on that later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that project-level benefit, a big-picture goal is to use the same base component library across multiple projects. All websites contain many of the same elements. There will be a header, footer, images, and buttons on every site we build. Before even having designs completed, we can already have a skeleton laid out. Additionally, this allows us to make sure we’re always being consistent in our work and adhere to best practices in usability and accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finding-the-right-tool&quot;&gt;Finding the Right Tool&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of great component library tools out there, but we needed to find one that would fit our (rather specific) needs. Some of the goals we kept in mind while looking for the best tool were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prioritizing integration with Drupal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using the same code for components library and Drupal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support for Twig (how we build our templates in Drupal)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supports our build processes (webpack, linting, image optimization, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y’all, I’m gonna be straight with you. Finding the right tool for this was &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. Many of the tools for component libraries out there are (logically) focused on supporting projects in React, Vue, or Angular. Our projects weren’t a logical use case for these kinds of technologies. It immediately became clear that there was probably no “out of the box” solution and we’d have to do at least some customization to fit our needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found a lot of blog posts and articles where teams had leveraged a component library and Drupal or integrated Twig with popular component library tools. Sadly, we didn’t find much explanation of &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to do it. (We’re looking to remedy that problem in Part 2 of this post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After tinkering with several solutions we finally settled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://storybook.js.org/&quot;&gt;Storybook&lt;/a&gt;. Storybook offered a more light-weight file structures than some others, uses webpack, and would work with other front-end technologies we’ll use in the future. Storybook also benefits from a large community that works to improve the product and create great add-ons. Most importantly, it’s adaptable enough to fit our use case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-storybook-to-work-for-us&quot;&gt;Getting Storybook to Work for Us&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend to Savas gave us a great starter project that included Twig integration to get us up and running. We heavily changed and adapted that into our setup. We’ll dig into specifics in a future post, but there were some challenges we faced along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-integrating-storybook-into-drupal&quot;&gt;1. Integrating Storybook into Drupal&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ultimately created a Storybook directory within our site’s theme directory. This allows all of the templates in our Drupal theme to access Storybook components within the same project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-using-twig&quot;&gt;2. Using Twig&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twig Loader has been the key to getting Storybook and Twig to work well together. It’s only necessary for us to load within Storybook itself and has allowed us to use Twig templates seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-custom-webpack-configuration&quot;&gt;3. Custom Webpack Configuration&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our theme directory, we created a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wepback.commons.js&lt;/code&gt; file that both the webpack config in our Drupal theme and the one in the Storybook directory could have access to. This allows for the styles/scripts Storybook to be compiled into bundles that both Storybook and our Drupal theme have access to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-integrating-tailwind&quot;&gt;4. Integrating Tailwind&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a team, we use &lt;a href=&quot;https://tailwindcss.com/&quot;&gt;Tailwind&lt;/a&gt;, a utility framework for CSS. It comes with its own needs in terms of webpack configuration and we fought a bit of a battle getting all plugins and configs to play nicely together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup we ultimately ended up with has worked great with some limitations. We’re still troubleshooting some issues with Storybook accessing our custom JS files. Fortunately, Drupal’s access to the scripts hasn’t been an issue, so we haven’t had our progress impeded too much as we tackle that lingering challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thoughts-at-the-halfway-point&quot;&gt;Thoughts at the Halfway Point&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is unique - it’s not a pre-mortem or post-mortem, it’s a….mid-mortem? We’ve already learned a lot, made some mistakes along the way, but are proud to say we have Storybook and Drupal working in tandem with one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Jump on Front-end&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest differences this approach made off the bat was the ability to immediately get started on building components on the front-end. We built JSON data models so we could populate our templates based on the data that would be coming from Drupal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the Drupal environment was ready, we slid our Storybook theme right in and started hooking up our templates to their respective paragraph types, and voilà!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting More Organized&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on making components reusable and focusing on atomic design principles has helped us be more efficient in our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great example of this is the use of “cards” on one project. This particular project features seven different types of cards. All share at least two common elements, some share many, some have elements that don’t exist on other cards at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each of those seven “types” of cards, each of &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; has multiple versions that show in different scenarios. They all ultimately reference one component file. In turn, that template can references some even smaller templates that change depending on the context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a Drupal perspective, most of our template files contain nothing but a reference and variable declarations to the appropriate storybook component. Nothing gets siloed or repeated. All roads lead back to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;card.twig&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Trending Topic card example&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/storybook-card-1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Core Team card example&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/storybook-card-2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Person card example&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/storybook-card-3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Event card example&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/storybook-card-4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Project card example&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/storybook-card-5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;News Update card example &quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/storybook-card-6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Featured Topic card example&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/storybook-card-7.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d love to say that everything has been easy and flawless, but you wouldn’t believe us anyway. There have been some challenges along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we seem to continually be refactoring component files to be &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; flexible and reusable as we continue to find use cases for them. We focused heavily on creating paragraph types in Storybook, but as we build other sections of our sites, we realize the shared styles and functionality can expand even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the same lines, finding the right balance on how to break everything down within the paradigm of atomic design is a challenge. I have found that some things that began as an “organism” should more realistically be considered “molecules”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another challenge has been creating templates that work appropriately for both Drupal and Storybook. What works to display something in Drupal might not work as well for Storybook. Overriding templates for fields changes the data flow so it becomes more necessary to pass Storybook literal templates as data instead of just data itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of writing this blog post, we’re still working on integrating all of our Storybook components into Drupal and getting sites ready for our clients to start adding content. Once we’ve finished and shipped our projects, we’ll do a post-mortem on what went well, what went badly, and what we learned from this experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, we’re going to provide you with some solid technical steps on getting Storybook up and running in Drupal, plus some advice to help you along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/10/11/storybook-pt-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/10/11/storybook-pt-1.html</guid>
        
        <category>storybook</category>
        
        <category>front-end-dev</category>
        
        <category>component-libraries</category>
        
        <category>twig</category>
        
        <category>drupal</category>
        
        <category>drupal-planet</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Code School Made Me a Better PM</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: before transitioning to the Digital Project Manager career, I spent ~6 months out of the year traveling internationally for work (for an amazing organization called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ewh.org&quot;&gt;Engineering World Health&lt;/a&gt; – yes, I’m biased, but check it out!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meant I spent a lot of time in countries in which I did not speak the local language (including Kinyarwanda, Swahili, Khmer, Nepali, and Mongolian). Before each 2-3 month trip, I’d learn some basic phrases (you know, the classics: “Hello,” “Where is the bathroom?”, and “Please, stop the bus, I need to get out!”). However, I found that for each new language, it took about a week for my ears to adjust to the new sounds and patterns so that I could reliably pick up words and phrases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Map depicting Maddy's travels&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/maddy-travels-map.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Those tiny red dots are areas I’ve lived, worked, and traveled over the past three years.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found that the same principle applies to working in web development. In my last blog post, I wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/22/top-5-things-to-know-to-speak-drupal.html&quot;&gt;Learning to Speak Drupal&lt;/a&gt;. Now, I’m reflecting on how learning the basics of the command line, git, and frontend languages made me a better advocate for clients, development teams, and a better project manager as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m both perpetually curious &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; respectful of my coworker’s time, I looked to a free, open-source code school called The Odin Project to begin learning the “basic phrases” of web development. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theodinproject.com&quot;&gt;The Odin Project&lt;/a&gt; teaches Ruby on Rails as a backend language and framework, while Savas works primarily with PHP/Drupal. However, I still found it to be a fantastic roadmap for learning the basics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theodinproject.com/courses/web-development-101&quot;&gt;Web Development 101&lt;/a&gt; course and would recommend it to anyone who prefers learning by doing (and failing and then doing again…). While working my way through the course, I built this groovy &lt;a href=&quot;https://maddybvh.github.io/etch-a-sketch/&quot;&gt;etch-a-sketch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Yoshi depicted on virtual etch-a-sketch&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/etch-a-sketch.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ro, a senior PM at Savas, used my etch-a-sketch to draw a killer rendition of Yoshi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also built this throwback, functional “solar-powered” &lt;a href=&quot;https://maddybvh.github.io/calculator/&quot;&gt;calculator&lt;/a&gt; from scratch using HTML, CSS, and JavaScript (#proud):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://maddybvh.github.io/calculator/&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500px&quot; style=&quot;border:none&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a blast and grew a whole new level of appreciation for Savas’s supportive frontend squad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Slack messages congratulating Maddy on her etch-a-sketch creation&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/maddy-front-end-slack.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s all just fun and games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my day-to-day job, the most valuable skill I’ve developed is comfort using the command line and git. One of my favorite ways to help my team is by removing blockers and addressing bottlenecks. Sometimes this is best done through project planning and capacity planning, and sometimes it’s best done by rolling up my sleeves and filling a needed role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I see it, project managers are the ultimate team players. Providing timely, manual QA of a bug fix branch before  code review and deployment to a staging site is one way that I’m able to help keep projects running on time and unblock team members. Other times I’m able to help troubleshoot – or, let’s be honest, at least recreate – a local stack issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also able to confidently answer questions including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the difference between a codebase and a database?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is a merge conflict?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the actual steps required to stage work for client review?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savas is developer founded and developer managed. It’s one of the things I like most about working here, and it jives well with my curious nature and technical tendencies. Learning just a tiny bit of programming has made me more confident in my ability to contribute to the work we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never became fluent in Kinyarwanda or Nepali, but I did learn enough to get around and occasionally impress the locals. I think about programming in the same way. While I may never become fluent in CSS or PHP, I’m learning enough to do QA locally, spot a complex feature request, and occasionally impress developers and technical clients with what I’ve picked up along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my main goals in life is to expand my comfort zone (professionally, and otherwise). Next on my list? I’d like to improve my vocabulary for the design phase of projects. I’ll be starting with reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Articulating-Design-Decisions-Communicate-Stakeholders/dp/1491921560&quot;&gt;Articulating Design Decisions&lt;/a&gt;, by Tom Greever, which comes recommended by Savas designer, &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/sean-oshea/&quot;&gt;Sean&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m always on the lookout for resources to expand my vocabulary and expertise. What do you do to expand your professional comfort zone?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/09/11/code-school-made-me-a-better-pm.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/09/11/code-school-made-me-a-better-pm.html</guid>
        
        <category>best-practices</category>
        
        <category>business</category>
        
        <category>productivity</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our Team Keeps Getting Bigger: Meet Kayla Morales</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As you know, we’ve been growing quite a bit these last few months &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/careers/&quot;&gt;(still are, if you want to join us!)&lt;/a&gt;. So it’s with great pleasure that we welcome our newest addition &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/kayla-morales/&quot;&gt;Kayla&lt;/a&gt; Morales to the Savas Labs team!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Welcome, welcome, welcome, welcome. - Jimmy Fallon&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/jimmy-fallon-welcome.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kayla joins as our newest Project Manager. In between her busy days onboarding with &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/maddy-bishop-van-horn/&quot;&gt;Maddy&lt;/a&gt;, getting acclimated to the office, and taking on projects of her own, we caught up and I asked some questions for us all to get to know her a bit better. So, without further ado, let’s meet Kayla!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Okay, Kayla, let’s just jump right in! Where did you go to college and what did you study?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I studied History with a minor in Technical &amp;amp; Professional Communications at Shippensburg University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, you’re a Pennsylvanian! Welcome to Durham! Tell me what you have been doing career-wise since graduation until now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to joining the Savas Labs team, I worked as a Copywriter &amp;amp; Digital Marketing Specialist at a small digital marketing agency in Pennsylvania. I mainly created content/copy, managed social media platforms, and oversaw local listings for clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relocating from PA and transitioning to a more technical agency; what made you choose Savas as your next career move?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/careers/&quot;&gt;Savas is a growing company&lt;/a&gt;, thriving at a rapid pace. I chose Savas because I wanted to be a part of an organization that is expanding, so I can grow alongside as a professional, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What were/are you most excited about joining the Savas Team?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a part of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/&quot;&gt;cohesive group&lt;/a&gt;, working alongside creative and hard-working individuals, and learning more about project management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Well, we are very glad you’re here! How is the Savas Team/office set-up/workflow different from what you’ve experienced in the past?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other places that I worked at prior to joining the Savas Team were very rigid, structured, and not very collaborative. Most of the time, my thoughts and ideas surrounding certain topics or projects were never taken into account. The first day I started working at Savas, I noticed how different of a work dynamic it is compared to my prior jobs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/mission-and-values/&quot;&gt;Savas is very much a united and communal workplace&lt;/a&gt;, which I greatly appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how Savas provides a platform for others to speak and voice their thoughts about projects or other important work-related topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What strengths do you bring to this team?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I believe my greatest strength is my desire to learn. Coming from a different background that didn’t center on project management, or web programming/development, it can be a challenge to get acquainted with a new industry / career field. But despite the challenges and learning curves, learning new things doesn’t intimidate me. I think the most imperative thing that any professional can do is have a zeal to learn new things, even if it may be out of their so-called “comfort zone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s one (of many) reasons you make such a great addition to this team! How are you enjoying The Triangle so far? Anything unique you’ve noticed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raleigh and Durham are such beautiful, fun cities. I’m looking forward to visiting their many attractions and (of course) visiting as many restaurants as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Savas team bonds during social outing.&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/savas-social-outing.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Kayla's first team outing to a local spot here in Durham!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anything else that you want folks to know about you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m really boring, but here it goes! &lt;em&gt;(Author’s note: as far as we can tell, Kayla is NOT boring.)&lt;/em&gt; I’ve just learned how to embroider—I know, I’m such a grandma—which I now absolutely love. I didn’t think I would get involved in this kind of hobby, but now I have thanks to a wonderful friend who taught me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love to read. So much so that in my junior year of college, I installed a Little Free Library in my college community for a class project. I’m super proud of it and enjoy visiting it whenever I visit Shippensburg. I’m always amazed at the amount of books that it is filled with. It definitely warms my heart to know that I’ve united the community (in some little way) through literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Little Free Library in Pennsylvania.&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/little-free-library.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Kayla’s Little Free Library packed full of good reads! Raise your hand if you think Savas should install a Little Free Library here in Durham?! 🙋🏽‍♀️&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s no surprise that I’m a massive nerd. I love watching old classic films whenever I can!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have a deep love for traveling. I’ve visited England, Netherlands, Germany, Austria, Switzerland, Italy, France, and Mexico. Fingers crossed, I plan on exploring more wonderful countries in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/08/05/our-team-keeps-getting-bigger-meet-kayla-morales.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/08/05/our-team-keeps-getting-bigger-meet-kayla-morales.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savas Expands Development Team: Meet Alex Manzo</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am beyond thrilled to join the Savas Labs team as a junior front-end developer. I came to Savas after a year working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://nete.com/&quot;&gt;NETE&lt;/a&gt;. Before that, I spent my days, nights, and weekends working in athletics video production. I’m probably the only member of the Savas team who could produce a live basketball broadcast without breaking a sweat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Alex on Elon's basketball hoop celebrating the championship&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/alex-championship.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Alex celebrating the championship!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to pursue a career in web development because I love to constantly be learning, solving problems, and the general thrill of seeing a project come to life. I was drawn to Savas specifically because of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/mission-and-values/&quot;&gt;mission and core values&lt;/a&gt;. I was particularly drawn to the idea of a company focused on this idea of “creating positive change.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stood out to me in part because of a personal side project - an &lt;a href=&quot;https://bathroom-finder.alexmanzo.me/&quot;&gt;All-Gender Bathroom Finder&lt;/a&gt;. This project started out of a desire to continue to hone web development skills both on the front and back-end, but I knew it would make a big difference for me to work on something I was personally invested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a non-binary person, going to the bathroom is a needlessly stressful experience. Have you ever been racked with anxiety standing outside bathrooms deciding which one is safer for you to use that day? I have 🙋‍♂! I wanted to create a tool to help me keep track of spaces where I know it’s safe to use the bathroom. Eventually, I’d love to continue adding to and improving it so the entire trans and non-binary community can have a tool for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing the Savas mission around creating positive change and projects like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/results/case-studies/pmp-civil-rights-map/&quot;&gt;Durham Civil and Human Rights History Map&lt;/a&gt; showed me that this was a place I could come work on projects and with clients I know I’ll care about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as other things you should know about me, consider this list a great primer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My personal favorite form of communication is in GIFs. Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/chris-russo/&quot;&gt;fearless leader&lt;/a&gt; even said “For realz, Alex makes me hate GIFs a little less”.
If that’s not a great compliment, I don’t know what is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;I am extremely talented. -Phoebe from Friends&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/phoebe-extremely-talented.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On Sundays in the fall, you can probably find me watching the New York Giants. After my grandpa passed away when I was young, I promised my dad I would take up the mantle and root for the team with him. It was cute when I was 7, but my spouse has told me it’s less cute now. Something about yelling at the television?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Disappointed NY Giants&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/disappointed-ny-giants.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve read Harry Potter so many times one of my books is literally broken in half. My spouse and I also make it a point to rack up first place finishes in Harry Potter trivia.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our household revolves around our two dogs, Jasper &amp;amp; Patch. The pair bring a delightful amount of dysfunction into day-to-day life. Jasper has already made a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavasLabs/status/1142097797895925761&quot;&gt;visit&lt;/a&gt; to Savas headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Alex and Jasper in Savas office&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/alex-jasper-in-office.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Jasper visited Savas on Bring Your Dog to Work Day. Will Jasper be the newest Savas team member?&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to be part of the Savas Team and get to work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Enough with the hellos; let's do this! -Bernie Sanders&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/bernie-sanders-hellos.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/07/30/savas-expands-development-team-meet-alex-manzo.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/07/30/savas-expands-development-team-meet-alex-manzo.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Should you contribute to open-source software? &lt;em&gt;It's complicated&lt;/em&gt;.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following article is the foundation for a 2019 Drupal GovCon session in the Business + Community track entitled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drupalgovcon.org/2019/program/sessions/should-you-contribute-open-source-its-complicated&quot;&gt;“Should you contribute to open source? It’s complicated.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that the &lt;em&gt;act of contributing&lt;/em&gt; to open-source software (OSS) is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/What-makes-it-difficult-for-you-to-contribute-to-an-open-source-project&quot;&gt;complicated&lt;/a&gt;. Having the requisite skills to perform the work and the time to navigate a community are substantial barriers, to name just two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever the fan of double entendres, I believe that whether OSS contribution is the &lt;em&gt;best usage of time and skill&lt;/em&gt; for professionals who work in OSS (read: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sdtimes.com/os/open-source-at-20-the-ubiquity-of-shared-code/&quot;&gt;everyone&lt;/a&gt;) is &lt;em&gt;also complicated&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my career (all in OSS, excluding my high school &lt;em&gt;sandwich artist&lt;/em&gt; days), my colleagues have held near unanimity that it’s in the organization’s best interest to contribute back to the OSS tools it uses. They’ve typically advocated doing so during company time (for brevity’s sake, from here on, I’ll refer to this as “flex time”). Beyond my anecdote, the data also show that a &lt;a href=&quot;https://insights.stackoverflow.com/survey/2019#developer-profile-_-contributing-to-open-source&quot;&gt;majority of software developers contribute&lt;/a&gt; at least occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the sections to follow, we’ll briefly look at the OSS ecosystem, analyzing both the motivations that drive and the barriers that challenge the highly-skilled individuals and organizations who contribute to OSS. We’ll also take a look at &lt;em&gt;some alternatives&lt;/em&gt; to OSS contribution and how we &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; use our limited (flex) time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-open-source-software-oss-contribution&quot;&gt;What Is Open-source Software (OSS) Contribution?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Redhat (who runs opensource.com and whose &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps?q=100EDavieSt,Raleigh,NC,27601&quot;&gt;HQ&lt;/a&gt; is in our backyard)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Open source software is software with source code that anyone can inspect, modify, and enhance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few examples of popular OSS projects that you’re perhaps familiar with (at least one of which you’re using right now) are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chromium.org/&quot;&gt;Google Chrome Browser&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://drupal.org/&quot;&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt; CMS and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; static site generator, the platform for the Savas website (at the time of writing this). In fact, much of the foundation of the internet is OSS. Anyone who has the requisite expertise can modify such programs; the access is free. Whether or not those modifications qualify as “enhancements,” much like beauty, is in the eye of the beholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposite end of the spectrum is closed-source software, which is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; publicly available to be modified and is almost always exclusively licensed by the company that owns and protects the proprietary code to consumers and businesses who use the product. A couple of examples of closed-source software that you may be familiar with are Adobe Creative Suite and Microsoft Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful OSS projects are highly utilized, and by design, foster substantial collaboration causing robust and complex communities to form around them. Let’s look at the stakeholders in those communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oss-stakeholders&quot;&gt;OSS Stakeholders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Warren Buffet holding a steak, get it?&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/steak-holder.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Memegenerator.com&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two fundamental stakeholders that comprise the contributors to an OSS community: individuals and organizations. Organizations are naturally comprised of individuals. Individuals either work for an organization that uses the OSS tools or represent themselves. When not employed by a company, individuals are either hobbyists or what I would argue is the more sustainable of the two, self-employed freelancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizations and individuals have some nuanced distinctions in their motivations and how they behave within OSS communities. A single contributor’s motivations can range from entirely self-promotional to solely altruistic, which depends largely on the individual and their circumstances. An organization’s incentives tend to be more systematic and structured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;individual-stakeholders-and-their-motivations&quot;&gt;Individual Stakeholders And Their Motivations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-full-width&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Richard Simmons pointing like only he can&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/richard-simmons-motivation.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Richard Simmons @ Reed College motivational AF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many things motivate us in the workplace; some irrespective of the type of work, while others are inextricably linked to it. We humans have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/what-is-the-need-to-belong-2795393&quot;&gt;deep desire to belong&lt;/a&gt; to a group, to be included, to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/onbeing/alain-de-botton-the-true-hard-work-of-love-and-relationships-aug2018#t=39:08&quot;&gt;accepted&lt;/a&gt;. For many individuals, this undergirds at least some of their motivation to contribute to an OSS project, and by extension, to become part of a community. Contribution can also positively influence one’s career opportunities by demonstrating proficiency publicly with a particular tool. Developing a professional network with other OSS professionals within the community can also be advantageous and complements the skills gained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, as Daniel Pink expresses in his seminal book Drive (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thersa.org/discover/videos/rsa-animate/2010/04/rsa-animate---drive#&quot;&gt;cartoon-animated with a sharpie if you prefer&lt;/a&gt;), significant motivations for knowledge workers across industries are &lt;strong&gt;autonomy&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;mastery&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;purpose&lt;/strong&gt;. In the best of circumstances, OSS contribution can check all three of these boxes if the contributor has some control over what they’re going to contribute. This Harvard Business School report exemplifies the demonstration of mastery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Companies that contribute and give back learn how to better use the open source software in their own environment. &lt;span&gt;Frank Nagle - HBS - &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbswk.hbs.edu/item/the-hidden-benefit-of-giving-back-to-open-source-software&quot;&gt;The Hidden Benefit of Giving Back to Open Source Software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A local favorite of mine, behavioral economist Dan Ariely, demonstrates the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/dan_ariely_what_makes_us_feel_good_about_our_work/transcript?language=en&quot;&gt;importance of “purpose”&lt;/a&gt;, which he refers to as “meaning” in experiments he’s conducted targeting knowledge workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;organization-stakeholders-and-their-motivations&quot;&gt;Organization Stakeholders And Their Motivations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some ways, organizations share motivations with individuals as they are a collective of them, or in the case of a U.S. corporation, a &lt;em&gt;very powerful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hYclXJTRzqU&quot;&gt;person&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, if you prefer. I don’t. However, I’ll focus on the motivations that are unique to organizations for the sake of comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An organization looks at self-preservation differently than an individual. An individual needs to eat, drink, sleep, and be be loved. An organization, to keep its doors open, has to do things like marketing, sales, recruiting, and the like. For agencies like ours who work with OSS, but whose business model is to serve clients, OSS contribution — not merely leveraging OSS in a build, but true contribution to a core project — requires either volunteer time, or company dedicated flex time to do the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_RMtnDaxmPw&quot;&gt;deep work&lt;/a&gt; of OSS contribution. There are rare opportunities in which project work fits well with an OSS contribution, but this is typically a serendipitous exception, not the norm. The flex time does not bring in revenue directly, so it represents a short-term opportunity cost to the organization of someone’s (usually a developer’s) time. The question is, is the investment worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;oss-contribution-marketing-and-sales-benefits-substantiated&quot;&gt;OSS Contribution Marketing And Sales Benefits. Substantiated?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizations may market OSS contribution as conferring a competitive advantage but, IMCO (correct), that advantage is often overstated. Differentiating one’s organization from its competitors &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the world of marketing and sales, and is just the game we all play. Try this overzealous marketing statement on for size that I referenced in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://events.drupal.org/neworleans2016/sessions/total-value-ownership-drupal-8-and-beyond&quot;&gt;Drupalcon talk in 2016&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At Chapter Three, our dedicated team of experts helped to build Drupal 8, and we are helping port modules to Drupal 8 daily. Our investment in Drupal 8 has given us unprecedented access to the latest Drupal 8 techniques and put us lightyears ahead of others agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps a touch too braggadocious? I’d be curious to know how that worked out for them. Also, “light years”: two words, and is, of course, a measure of distance, so I’m not sure exactly &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; that puts them on the map, but seemingly not “&lt;em&gt;light years&lt;/em&gt;” ahead in grammar compared to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/savaslabs/savaslabs.github.io/blob/source/hooks/pre-commit#L45-L63&quot;&gt;“others agencies”&lt;/a&gt; ;)  &lt;a href=&quot;https://us2.campaign-archive.com/?u=84a5d97487adda9f8f52224e2&amp;amp;id=04a3ce3d49&amp;amp;e=83a6cb0714&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/rant&amp;gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Partial dig notwithstanding, we appreciate your support in making Drupal 8 better &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chapterthree.com/&quot;&gt;Chapter 3&lt;/a&gt; – we undoubtedly benefited from your work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediacurrent.com/blog/why-should-companies-support-drupal/&quot;&gt;others in our industry, like Mediacurrent&lt;/a&gt;, do &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediacurrent.com/blog/how-organizations-can-give-back-open-source-projects-and-why/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; as well (including &lt;a href=&quot;/results/open-source/&quot;&gt;us&lt;/a&gt;). Like Chapter Three, Mediacurrent is also well known in the Drupal community as a perennial contributor, and I have a lot of respect for them as an organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While contribution demonstrates &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; skill with a tool, it is only on rare occasions that a specific OSS contribution is a meaningful distinction – decision-makers who determine what consultant to hire for a project usually don’t have the experience to understand what the OSS contribution represents and, in most cases, do not care. Rather, OSS contribution is part of a whole package of being a good standing digital corporate citizen, but it’s rarely the chief decision-maker in a sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;oss-contribution-recruiting-impact&quot;&gt;OSS Contribution Recruiting Impact&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;companies that pay employees to contribute to open source are improving their image and, potentially, their ability to recruit top talent. &lt;span&gt;Frank Nagle - HBS - &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbswk.hbs.edu/item/the-hidden-benefit-of-giving-back-to-open-source-software&quot;&gt;The Hidden Benefit of Giving Back to Open Source Software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the knowledge economy, an organization’s most valuable resource is its people, and providing the opportunity to contribute helps with employee satisfaction (and therefore, retention) for the contributor. Savas Labs has had the chance to &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/tag/team/&quot;&gt;grow throughout 2019 consistently&lt;/a&gt;. With that fortune, I have spent a fair amount of time conversing with applicants, a majority of whom express an interest in the opportunity to contribute to OSS and that they appreciate &lt;a href=&quot;/results/open-source/&quot;&gt;how we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; that at Savas&lt;/a&gt;. So, it stands to reason, to remain a competitive workplace, it has become somewhat of an expectation that OSS contribution is part of company time. Marketing these contributions entices future applicants, which can be tremendously valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue (I am, quite cogently I might add) that, recruiting, employee satisfaction, and retention confer the most significant organizational benefits from flex time OSS contribution. Existing and prospective team members &lt;em&gt;do understand&lt;/em&gt; OSS and are intrigued by an environment that will help them contribute to it for all the reasons mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;oss-contribution-financial-impact&quot;&gt;OSS Contribution Financial Impact&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we’ve learned from Pink is that people aren’t as professionally motivated by money as we might think they are. When the work requires at least “rudimentary cognitive skill,” an individual tends to focus on other emotionally fulfilling aspects of their work. In most cases, OSS contributors within a company don’t see much difference in their compensation regardless of the amount of time given for contribution. Organizations, however, typically have more financially-oriented goals and have a greater onus to serve their stakeholders (employees, owners, and investors). Therefore, necessarily, they need to focus on money more than individuals do. To “take the issue of money off the table” as Pink suggests, those of us who run organizations need to be financially competent and transparent so that finances are not an issue non-owning team members need to worry about. All this to say, there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; challenges to striking a healthy balance of company flex time, and it is of utmost importance for organizations to justify the return on investment from a host of perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;challenges-to-oss-contribution&quot;&gt;Challenges To OSS Contribution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all things in life not created equally, the ability to contribute to OSS is no exception. To his credit and admitting to the errors of his previous oversight (with some assistance from the diversity and inclusion team, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/7rbUyv3hYDc?t=307&quot;&gt;others he’s employed&lt;/a&gt;), the creator of Drupal, Dries Buytaert, writes well to the fact that &lt;a href=&quot;https://dri.es/the-privilege-of-free-time-in-open-source&quot;&gt;OSS contribution is a tremendously privileged activity&lt;/a&gt;.  Therefore, who gets to contribute is not evenly distributed in society, and neither are the advantages that come along with having those public contributions to reference. Others have said it well in the past:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It takes time and mentorship to contribute to open source, and not everyone has those two things. &lt;span&gt;Mark Lavin @ All Things Open 2015 then of Caktus Group&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I’ve referenced three other (white) men talking about privilege. Noted :thinking:.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interviewers – the Savas Labs recruiting team is no exception – will often ask about, and certainly search for without asking, public proof of expertise. OSS contributions are the most common and relevant bits of this information. It is a data point that we’ve learned to appreciate the embedded privilege that may be associated with it and judge accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-not-oss-contribution-then-what-are-the-alternatives&quot;&gt;If not OSS contribution, then what are the alternatives?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our profession, we must continuously prioritize how to best use our limited time in a way that’s most rewarding to the relevant stakeholders to our organization: our team members, partners, and depending on your perspective, to society at large. This is the area I probably spend the most time thinking about, and yet also seems to be the most challenging from which to derive clarity. Many others have been thinking about these things for a long time as well. Here are a few approaches out there:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement a volunteer day&lt;/strong&gt;: We’ve recently added a Community Service day to our company benefits. This a good way to empower people with the autonomy to give back in however they see most fit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start an innovation lab&lt;/strong&gt;: Our neighbors and good friends one block to the north, Viget, instituted something they call “&lt;a href=&quot;https://pointlesscorp.com/&quot;&gt;Pointless Corp&lt;/a&gt;” in which, when team members have flex time, they may choose to build useful or fun projects &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.viget.com/articles/making-things-just-because/&quot;&gt;just because&lt;/a&gt;, in their case, with a unique brand of “pointless” irreverence. While clearly not aiming for Pink’s &lt;strong&gt;purpose&lt;/strong&gt; of the three main drivers for knowledge workers, Pointless Corp provides Vigeters an opportunity to develop &lt;strong&gt;mastery&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;autonomously&lt;/strong&gt;. As a wise,  Meatloaf once said, yes, the same Meatloaf who &lt;em&gt;would do anything for love&lt;/em&gt;: “two out of three ain’t bad.” Such &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k5hWWe-ts2s&quot;&gt;passion :cupid: that Meatloaf!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide autonomous structure&lt;/strong&gt;: Our neighbors and good friends one block to the south, thoughtbot, have something they call “&lt;a href=&quot;https://thoughtbot.com/playbook/our-company/time&quot;&gt;investment time&lt;/a&gt;” in which they give their team members guidance on what to do within some parameters, but it’s primarily up to the team member to decide what they’ll work on. They dedicate their entire Friday each week (with few exceptions) to investment time. This commitment is impressive, and as far as I can tell from speaking to their team members, something they really appreciate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work on pro bono projects&lt;/strong&gt;: In other words, providing consultation and services for free for a mission-driven organization or one that has limited resources (often a nonprofit). These projects can be highly beneficial to the receiving organization and can give purpose to the delivering team when the services they provide make an impact. We had a great experience with &lt;a href=&quot;/results/case-studies/pmp-civil-rights-map/&quot;&gt;Barbara Lau and the Pauli Murray Project&lt;/a&gt;. Merging the often different work styles and pace can present challenges. I recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ragtag-notes/tech-for-social-impact-6359bb241fc&quot;&gt;this resource&lt;/a&gt; provided by Ragtag, an organization whose purpose is to &lt;em&gt;“amplify progressive organizing in innovative and high-impact ways”&lt;/em&gt; on how to have a successful partnership. At Savas, we are in the process of formalizing an initiative to take on at least one pro bono project per year. More details to come in a follow-up post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you feel about these options? Does your company do something different, or do you have an idea of a good usage of flex time? Please let us know via &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSd4hGMEcf-m-SD4AYZhfVZXAjrVPIZTJAxBNFK9iL1Q7o-hvg/viewform&quot;&gt;this &lt;strong&gt;super short&lt;/strong&gt; survey&lt;/a&gt; or by leaving a &lt;a href=&quot;#js-comments&quot;&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt;. We’ll share the results in a follow-up post when we’ve collected some data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-should-you-contribute-to-open-source&quot;&gt;So, Should You Contribute To Open-Source?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s our hot take given the array of incentives, challenges, and goals of organizations and individuals on whether or not you should contribute to OSS? Well, I wouldn’t be a proper consultant if I didn’t answer this with a resounding: &lt;strong&gt;it depends&lt;/strong&gt;, now would I?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t try to be prescriptive for all individuals as to what they &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do with their free time, but I would be remiss not to point out again that, in general, software designers and engineers are a very privileged group. If your goal is to “give back,” I would encourage you to ask yourself if those you want to help the most are other software developers and if not, how you can best use your resources to help whoever else it may be. Ultimately, OSS contribution is a good deed; sharing is caring. I have had opportunities to do sponsored OSS contribution and have also volunteered my time, though even &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; donations come with perks :eyes: :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;jekyll-twitter-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Bicycles on shirt: ✔️ &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/crocs?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#crocs&lt;/a&gt; on swag socks for being a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gatsbyjs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@gatsbyjs&lt;/a&gt; maintainer: ✔️  Flare dialed up to 💯: ✔️ With our powers combined... it&amp;#39;s going to be a great afternoon! &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/buildwithgatsby?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#buildwithgatsby&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/6fuNuJQXX5&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/6fuNuJQXX5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Savas Labs (@SavasLabs) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavasLabs/status/1045386497065701382?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;September 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an organization’s perspective, it depends on your company goals. Generally speaking, if you’re able to contribute to OSS, you should. On balance, contributing to something that gives value to others for free while improving your team’s job satisfaction and career options presents a win-win for the community and the contributor. Given the importance of your people, improving happiness has &lt;a href=&quot;https://warwick.ac.uk/newsandevents/pressreleases/new_study_shows/&quot;&gt;serious productivity implications&lt;/a&gt;, and improving recruiting quality and efficiency also have substantial payoffs, as it’s where we invest much of our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your organization seeks to benefit society more broadly with its flex time, a goal of ours at Savas Labs, we believe there are more powerful ways to consider beyond OSS contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/07/23/should-you-contribute-to-open-source.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/07/23/should-you-contribute-to-open-source.html</guid>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
        <category>open-source</category>
        
        <category>drupal</category>
        
        <category>business</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savas Brings on Another Front-end Developer</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-am-i&quot;&gt;Who am I?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello Savas Labs fans! My name is &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/madeline-streilein/&quot;&gt;Madeline Streilein&lt;/a&gt;, and I am one of Savas’ two brand new Junior Front-end Developers (&lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/alex-manzo/&quot;&gt;Alex Manzo&lt;/a&gt; also joined our burgeoning front-end squad under the tutelage of Anne Tomasevich - keep an eye out for their introduction). Some random facts about me: I love stone fruit, humidity, satirical news, and using Slack notation on all messaging platforms. I also opened a day spa in my home when I was in elementary school. It wasn’t &lt;em&gt;_not_&lt;/em&gt; profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-did-i-come-from&quot;&gt;Where did I come from?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.projectshift.io/&quot;&gt;Project Shift&lt;/a&gt;, if you haven’t heard, is a software engineering fellowship here in Durham. I am a proud graduate of Cohort 5. Prior to Project Shift, I came from the land of electoral politics, a field that relies heavily on technology (from data analytics and predictions to voter contact and volunteer recruitment) to mobilize voters and volunteers in the days, weeks, and months leading up to an election. In my most recent role, I ran a statewide peer-to-peer texting program to get North Carolinians to the polls. I experienced first hand how thoughtful technology can catalyze civic engagement, and on the flip side, how platforms that weren’t built with the user in mind could cause enough frustration to dissuade volunteer participation and annoy an on-the-fence electorate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-am-i-choosing-to-sit-behind-a-computer-when-i-could-be-hitting-the-pavement-or-training-organizers&quot;&gt;Why am I choosing to sit behind a computer when I could be hitting the pavement or training organizers?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I ask myself, possibly more frequently than I’d prefer, what is the best use of my time and potential skills? Am I contributing enough to causes that matter? Am I contributing in a way that is actually helpful and not harmful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer at which I’ve finally arrived is this: I believe technology has the potential to alter our habits as individuals, as a society, and as a species positively, more quickly, efficiently, and sustainably than through other means of change that may come to mind. I knew I had to switch industries to help build better solutions. Using technology to maximize positive impact, I learned through the interview process, is also part of a developing vision at Savas Labs. Stay tuned for an upcoming announcement with more specific articulation of those goals from team leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-did-i-choose-savas&quot;&gt;Why did I choose Savas?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose Savas for many reasons — especially the team. I’ve seen my coworkers practice and exemplify the &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/mission-and-values/&quot;&gt;values&lt;/a&gt; we define on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;, ones that drive me as well. How can one &lt;em&gt;_not_&lt;/em&gt; feel welcomed, empowered to excel, and ask for what they need in the onboarding process when they receive Slack messages like this from remote colleagues?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Slack screenshot&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/savas-welcome.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Senior Project Manager, Ro Wang, greets me warmly in a private message on Slack.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teammates bring to the table many things, in equal parts tangible and intangible, resulting in a highly productive, respectful, creative, and collaborative environment of humans who work diligently for our clients. I recognized that before I started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my last campaign wrapped up, I knew I would only be fulfilled if I went to work each day for a company that considers the community it operates within, and the unique responsibility it has to contribute (beyond the paid services it came into existence to provide). I was pleased to learn that at Savas Labs, every full-time employee is afforded one day of PTO for community service at an organization of our choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not as significant a factor in my job search, humor in the workplace is definitely a plus. Savas incorporates dad jokes (and other actual humor) into our weekly meetings, so I’ll just leave these here . . .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question: Why did the functional component feel lost?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: Because it didn’t know what &lt;em&gt;state&lt;/em&gt; it was in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question:  Why did the child component have such great self-esteem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: Because its parent kept giving it &lt;em&gt;props&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/07/03/savas-brings-on-another-front-end-developer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/07/03/savas-brings-on-another-front-end-developer.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adventures in Estimation: Accuracy and Strategy at Savas Labs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Excellent project management starts with accurate project time estimation and is important for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accurate time estimates assist in setting milestones and managing capacity when project planning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The accuracy (or lack thereof) of your time assessment will inform other’s perception of your reliability and competence as a project manager/company.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time estimates almost always have a significant impact on the financial success of a project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bottom-line-time-estimations-matter-a-lot&quot;&gt;Bottom line: Time estimations matter. A lot.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all too common to underestimate the amount of time needed for a project. Often, this is due to unanticipated challenges, requests for additional features, or unscheduled urgent tasks that occasionally pop up. Even so, estimates remain a key to success in any company—most especially ours, and we strive to keep them accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other things to keep in mind when considering estimates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimates are different from proposals or contracts (read: we estimate in time, not dollars).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimates are not definites.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good estimates take time, discovery, and vetting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimates are ultimately essential to both planning and financial success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Something to be wary of&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90313102/how-to-get-better-at-estimating-your-time&quot;&gt;The Planning Fallacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Planning Fallacy is failing to consider how long it’s taken to complete similar tasks in the past and assuming that we won’t run into any complications that will cause delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are known knowns; there are things we know we know. We also know there are known unknowns; that is to say, we know there are some things we do not know. But there are also unknown unknowns–the ones we don’t know we don’t know.  &lt;span&gt;- Donald Rumsfeld&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a deep dive into our past time estimates (for a presentation at our recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/08/savas-retreat-yo-self.html&quot;&gt;ReTreat Yo Self&lt;/a&gt; team retreat) and comparing to our actual spent time we concluded that as a company:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;calculating&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/calculating.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We like even numbers! (We also love a good &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palindrome&quot;&gt;palindrome&lt;/a&gt;, hence our name).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We’ve done a pretty good job, but as always, there is room for improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fight the planning fallacy:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge we (and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/specstimate/why-are-humans-so-bad-at-estimating-4b4290f83716&quot;&gt;the majority&lt;/a&gt;) face is the planning fallacy. So, here are a few suggestions for fighting the planning fallacy (adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90313102/how-to-get-better-at-estimating-your-time&quot;&gt;this helpful article&lt;/a&gt; and my own experience):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data talks.&lt;/strong&gt; And history tends to repeat itself. So use historical data to help make the most accurate estimations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do three estimates.&lt;/strong&gt; Best-case, worst-case, and most likely. Pro tip: assume your initial estimate is “best-case.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check the calendar.&lt;/strong&gt; Take into account the big picture. What other projects will you be working on at these same times? Who will be on vacation and unable to work on the project for a week?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think in “Work Weeks.”&lt;/strong&gt; When we think of how many days we have until a project is due, we often think in actual days not in “work days.” Count only the Monday-Friday days in your estimation. More on &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/ro-wang/&quot;&gt;Ro’s&lt;/a&gt; idea of “Work Weeks” coming soon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FUDGE it!&lt;/strong&gt; Use a fudge ratio:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Estimate the time it will take to do near-future tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Track the actual time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sum the estimates and the actual spent time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Divide the total spent time by the total estimated time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voilà! A fudge ratio! Apply that to future estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phone a friend.&lt;/strong&gt; Call on a coworker or another project manager. When estimating a project they aren’t working on, they are likely to give a far more realistic estimation than you would.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One word: RANGES&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t estimate in perfect numbers, give a range to account for unknowns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Started from the bottom and now…&lt;/strong&gt; Estimate at the low point of your day. That is to say, don’t do estimations when you’ve just had the most delicious lunch, your calendar is free, your inbox is near-empty, and you’re feeling high on life. You’ll be feeling over-optimistic about everything, including your time estimations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revisit&lt;/strong&gt;. After wading into a project, take a look back and revisit initial estimates. You know what they say: “measure twice, cut once.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-we-foster-estimation-success&quot;&gt;How we foster estimation success&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project typically fits into one of two broad categories: one in which we have a high degree of familiarity, and whose scope we understand well, and those we don’t. As discussed, with the former, we use historical records to hone in tightly on the expected efforts. That’s simple. In the latter case, in which the client’s vision is not fully articulated (and this is where we provided the most value), we have learned it’s in both parties best interest to perform a strategy phase upfront. We often call it a discovery, or planning and have found it to be instrumental in getting all stakeholders the same page and reducing risk. Once we’ve elicited all the information we can from conversations with stakeholders and any relevant user testing, we then focus internally. In conjunction with the project manager, the tech lead on a given project is responsible for laying out the plan to execute the project from start to finish. Once the tech lead has produced this detailed document, we have a “designated dissenter” internal meeting in which the goal of one teammate is to pick apart any &lt;em&gt;potentially false&lt;/em&gt; assumptions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/How-does-the-saying-about-assuming-something-go&quot;&gt;you know what they say about those&lt;/a&gt;) made by the tech lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;calculating&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/rbg-dissent.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This direct, constructive feedback is something that I would only consider within a team with a substantial “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/justin-bariso/google-spent-years-studying-effective-teams-this-single-quality-contributed-most-to-their-success.html&quot;&gt;psychological safety&lt;/a&gt;,” which we &lt;a href=&quot;/company/mission-and-values/&quot;&gt;work hard to cultivate and sustain&lt;/a&gt; at Savas. The feedback is a gift that helps avoid potential future pitfalls, but a person will only hear it from someone they trust and know has shared  goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we complete the internal work, we produce one of the most beneficial outputs from the discovery process: a more detailed plan with a more accurate schedule and budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting more accurate time expectations is better for everyone because we create the necessary space—and far less anxiety and pressure—to do better quality work. It creates reliability for the client, for ourselves and our coworkers and generally keeps everything running smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/05/14/adventures-in-estimation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/05/14/adventures-in-estimation.html</guid>
        
        <category>best-practices</category>
        
        <category>business</category>
        
        <category>productivity</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savas Hires a Marketing Coordinator</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, world! (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%22Hello,_World!%22_program&quot;&gt;is that right?&lt;/a&gt;) My name is &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/jordan-nelson/&quot;&gt;Jordan&lt;/a&gt;, and I’m the newest addition to the Savas Team. I’ve joined as the Marketing Coordinator!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be working on—you guessed it—all things marketing! Blog posts (some additional exciting posts are coming very soon), social media (come say hi &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavasLabs?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Eauthor&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/savaslabs/?modal=admin_todo_tour&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/company/savas-labs/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and events will be my domain. Plus some other exciting things we may have up our sleeves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Oh boy! This is gonna be good, I can tell. -Dory&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/oh-boy-nemo.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I come from a social media/email marketing background—working in higher education admissions and marketing offices, respectively, as well as the online retail space—and I’m very excited to jump in as part of this very talented Savas Labs team. I’m working to bring you quality content from all of us, keeping you up-to-date on all things Savas and helping get the word out about the great things we do here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned quickly, that here at Savas, music preferences are taken VERY seriously (especially locally in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/durham/&quot;&gt;Durham office&lt;/a&gt;). I was warned that music was a big part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/careers/&quot;&gt;Savas culture (It’s great here—you should come work with us, too!)&lt;/a&gt; and that the “rules” include the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We give &lt;em&gt;all kinds&lt;/em&gt; of music a chance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anyone can &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavasLabs/status/1084825113080578048&quot;&gt;veto any song&lt;/a&gt; at any time, no questions asked&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We always encourage song requests/suggestions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew immediately that my first suggestion was going to make an impression on this music-loving team (and I had learned that &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/chris-russo/&quot;&gt;someone&lt;/a&gt; on the team had an affinity for pop, specifically of the 90’s/2000’s variety).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Challenge accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggestion: &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/track/2BgEsaKNfHUdlh97KmvFyo&quot;&gt;2002 by Anne-Marie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friends, I’m so glad to report that — much like me taking the position here — it was a great choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;take a bow&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/take-a-bow.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/29/savas-hires-a-marketing-coordinator.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/29/savas-hires-a-marketing-coordinator.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Top 5 Things You Need To Know To Speak Drupal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Oh, hello there. I’m Savas Lab’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/maddy-bishop-van-horn/&quot;&gt;newest project manager&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to being new to Savas, I’m also a Drupal beginner. Before joining Savas, I had experience with several other CMSes (Wordpress, Craft, Joomla!, and Umbraco, in addition to a couple of custom Rails apps.) I didn’t know much about Drupal, but I’d heard enough rumors to be a little afraid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;The learning curve for popular CMSs&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/drupal-learning-curve.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Often shared image, source unknown.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve learned more about Drupal, I’ve come to appreciate that it is an incredibly powerful and flexible CMS and there’s a great community of commercial companies and volunteers who help to build and support it. My coworkers at Savas have helped me overcome the first hurdle in learning to work with Drupal: &lt;strong&gt;understanding Drupal terminology.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we dive in, I’d like to extend a huge thank you to Anne and &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/company/chris-russo/&quot;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; for their mentorship and their contributions to this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;drupal-terminology&quot;&gt;Drupal Terminology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit it: Drupal terminology is not very intuitive. This article lists the key terms and concepts that I’ve found necessary to get started. I’ll break it into five categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drupal code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taxonomy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Views&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-drupal-code&quot;&gt;1. DRUPAL CODE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Drupal? When we discuss the software package itself, we usually refer to one of the three subsections of code that have specific and distinct purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;drupal-core&quot;&gt;Drupal Core&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The codebase that makes up the basic “core” functionality of Drupal. It’s open source and updated consistently by the Drupal community. When writing this, Drupal 8 was the latest, stable version. The move from Drupal 7 to 8 is an investment, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/2017/11/08/cost-of-drupal-7.html&quot;&gt;it’s worth it&lt;/a&gt; and represents the last time such a substantial effort will be required to upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;modules&quot;&gt;Modules&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A module is a directory of code that extends Drupal features/functionality. Drupal core comes with some modules, and many others are freely available to be downloaded. The Drupal community develops and shares these modules outside of core and they are often referred to as “contrib” (short for contributed). If needed, developers can create &lt;strong&gt;custom&lt;/strong&gt; modules for specific functionality for a given client or project. &lt;em&gt;(Wordpress translation: Modules are like plugins, although they generally require more development knowledge to install and maintain.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;themes&quot;&gt;Themes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Theme is the part of the Drupal codebase that determines how the site and its content are displayed. Theme code includes HTML markup, CSS, JavaScript, and Drupal configuration files. Savas Labs’s clients nearly always require custom theme development, and fortunately Drupal supports an efficient, sophisticated means to build off of or “extend” base themes which reduces the effort to develop and maintain custom themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-content&quot;&gt;2. CONTENT&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content refers to the copy, images, and other media that make up a website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;content-type&quot;&gt;Content type&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A collection of fields created and defined by a developer via code or a site builder via the web admin interface. Each field has a set data type, limits, and display specifications. Drupal Core comes with some basic content types, like “article” and “basic page.” Drupal core ships with a couple of basic content types and site builders may define any number of additional content types as the site requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;node&quot;&gt;Node&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A piece of content created by a content editor. Each node has an associated content type. We can display nodes in a variety of ways across the site (we can think of it as a page, although it can be presented in other ways too. These display options are configured by developers by using &lt;strong&gt;views&lt;/strong&gt; - more on that below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paragraph&quot;&gt;Paragraph&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paragraphs are a powerful feature of Drupal 8 that did not exist in previous versions. Site builders may define Paragraph types, and they can have fields that include text, media, buttons, and more. (I repeat: paragraphs are not just for text.) I like to think of Paragraphs as components that admins can add to a &lt;strong&gt;node&lt;/strong&gt; (which, remember, we can think of as a page). Developers can add &lt;strong&gt;paragraph&lt;/strong&gt; fields to &lt;strong&gt;content types&lt;/strong&gt; to allow content editors to add a variety of &lt;strong&gt;paragraph types&lt;/strong&gt; to a node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- To be honest this seems too complex for beginners - maybe linking to a resource or having an animated GIF inline here to show what a paragraph is would go a long way to help beginners --&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;blocks&quot;&gt;Blocks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blocks are a way to put content in different regions of the site. They can be turned on and off for different pages. Take the example of a sidebar with three distinct pieces of content in it: “latest news”, “relevant content” and “ newsletter signup”. The &lt;strong&gt;region&lt;/strong&gt; would be the sidebar, and the three distinct pieces of content (“latest news”, “relevant content” and “newsletter signup”) would each be a &lt;strong&gt;block&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-taxonomy&quot;&gt;3. TAXONOMY&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxonomy is an essential and powerful part of Drupal. It is a system for classification that Drupal uses to define relationships between content. Think tags and keywords associated with a blog article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;vocabulary&quot;&gt;Vocabulary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vocabulary is a taxonomy type. Like content types, Vocabularies are a defined collection of fields and can have visible pages, but often they do not. Vocabularies are meant to be “tags” for content rather than pieces of content themselves. However, developers can define a vocabulary using any collection of fields, so it is technically possible for a Vocabulary to show up as a page, just uncommon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;term&quot;&gt;Term&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An item within a Vocabulary. You can think of a term as a “tag,” although they can have additional fields, as I mentioned above. &lt;strong&gt;Terms&lt;/strong&gt; are to &lt;strong&gt;Vocabularies&lt;/strong&gt; as &lt;strong&gt;nodes&lt;/strong&gt; are to &lt;strong&gt;content types&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-users&quot;&gt;4. USERS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Drupal’s strengths compared to other CMSes is its highly customizable user permissions and roles. But what does that mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;user&quot;&gt;User&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A user is anyone interacting with the site. Users can be &lt;strong&gt;anonymous&lt;/strong&gt; (any site visitor who is not logged in) or &lt;strong&gt;authenticated&lt;/strong&gt; (a visitor who logged in with an account).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;role&quot;&gt;Role&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A role is a defined type of user with assigned permissions. &lt;strong&gt;Anonymous&lt;/strong&gt; is one role. &lt;strong&gt;Authenticated&lt;/strong&gt; users can be given any number of defined roles, for example: “logged-in user”, “content creator”, and “administrator”. Administrators can create and customize as many roles as they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;permission&quot;&gt;Permission&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Permissions are levels of access that can be granted to roles by site administrators. Each &lt;strong&gt;role&lt;/strong&gt; can have a different view and edit permissions (e.g. “view published content”, “administer users”, “create new content”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-views&quot;&gt;5. VIEWS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drupal Views is one of the more powerful features of a Drupal site. It gives site administrators a high level of control and sophistication for grouping and presenting content across the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;views-module&quot;&gt;Views Module&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Views module allows administrators and site designers to create, manage, and display lists of content. Each list managed by the views module is known as a &lt;strong&gt;view&lt;/strong&gt;, and the output of a view is known as a &lt;strong&gt;display&lt;/strong&gt;. Admins can create displays in either block or page form, and a single view may have multiple displays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;view-mode&quot;&gt;View Mode&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;strong&gt;Views module&lt;/strong&gt;, developers can configure each &lt;strong&gt;content type&lt;/strong&gt; to have various &lt;strong&gt;view modes&lt;/strong&gt;. With view modes, admins can output a &lt;strong&gt;node&lt;/strong&gt; in a specific format with a particular set of fields. This format is known as a &lt;strong&gt;display&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a developer may make a “Preview” view mode, which will display a subset of the fields of a given &lt;strong&gt;content type&lt;/strong&gt;. By editing the fields of the node, content editors can change the content displayed in the “Preview” view mode. Another good example of a view mode that a developer may configure is a “search result” view mode, which will define, for each content type, how to display that content on the search page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good news: we made it! I won’t claim that you’re now completely fluent in Drupal, but you should have the foundation to understand and talk about the building blocks of a Drupal site with a developer or site builder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you also new to Drupal? Or are you a Drupal pro? Either way, leave a comment below with your favorite resources.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/22/top-5-things-to-know-to-speak-drupal.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/22/top-5-things-to-know-to-speak-drupal.html</guid>
        
        <category>drupal</category>
        
        <category>drupal8</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Savas Brings On (another) Project Manager</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Faithful readers of the Savas Blog, please welcome Maddy to the Savas Team! :wave: We are so excited that she’s here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maddy comes to us from premier Digital Agency, &lt;a href=&quot;https://viget.com&quot;&gt;Viget&lt;/a&gt;, by way of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ewh.org&quot;&gt;Engineering World Health&lt;/a&gt;—a non-profit that uses the skills of students and professionals to improve health care in low-income countries. During her time there, she traveled the globe managing teams of student-engineers working on medical equipment in places like Rwanda, Nepal, and Cambodia—how awesome is that?!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Outdoor meetings together at our airbnb&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/maddy-rwanda-mt-bisoke.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;On the rim of Mt Bisoke in Rwanda (home of the mountain gorillas!)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maddy has project management skills like you wouldn’t believe and we knew she would be a perfect fit for the Savas Labs Team (&lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/careers/&quot;&gt;Think you could be the perfect fit, too? You’re in luck, we’re hiring!&lt;/a&gt;). Her attention to detail, organizational skills, and self-motivated nature a great partner on any project and we’re excited for &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/results/&quot;&gt;current partners&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/services/&quot;&gt;new clients&lt;/a&gt; to get the chance to meet Maddy. We know they will be as impressed as we are!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: Maddy’s very first day on the job wasn’t from &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/contact/&quot;&gt;our Durham, NC office&lt;/a&gt; where she works from, but spent on a plane flying to &lt;a href=&quot;https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/08/savas-retreat-yo-self.html&quot;&gt;our latest Team Retreat&lt;/a&gt;—in Austin, Texas! Talk about an exciting first day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;blog-image-large&quot;&gt;
&lt;img alt=&quot;Outdoor meetings together at our airbnb&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/blog/maddy-austin-retreat.jpg&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Hard at work at ReTreat Yo Self.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fun fact about Maddy: She’s a foster dog mom. She’s making an impact in her community by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.carolinaadoptabulls.com&quot;&gt;fostering dogs&lt;/a&gt; and loving them well until (and after) they find a fur-ever home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maddy, we are glad you’re here!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/10/savas-welcomes-maddy-bishop-van-horn.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://savaslabs.com/2019/04/10/savas-welcomes-maddy-bishop-van-horn.html</guid>
        
        <category>team</category>
        
        <category>company-culture</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
